<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Natvral and morall questions and answers. Intermingled with many prettie and pleasant riddles, and darke sentences / written by A.P. ; with a manner of ordering the body for health through euery month of the yeare, and for dieting it for a seuen-night after blood-letting.  Written in Latin verse by Ioachimus Camerarius.</title>
            <author>A. P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19054.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94569</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">72799809</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 72799809</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184116</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07975)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2229:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Natvral and morall questions and answers. Intermingled with many prettie and pleasant riddles, and darke sentences / written by A.P. ; with a manner of ordering the body for health through euery month of the yeare, and for dieting it for a seuen-night after blood-letting.  Written in Latin verse by Ioachimus Camerarius.</title>
                  <author>A. P.</author>
                  <author>Camerarius, Joachim, 1534-1598 Victvs et cultvs ratio.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[140] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Adam Islip.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Victvs et cvltvs ratio exposita quatuor in singulos menses versibus, per Ioachimum Camerarium" at end p. 135-138.</note>
                  <note>Ornament on t.p. ; headpieces ; tailpieces ; initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁸ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages torn and have print show-through, error in register.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Riddles --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Aphorisms and apothegms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Questions and answers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184116:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184116:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NATVRAL and Morall Queſtions and Anſweres. Intermingled with many prettie and pleaſant Riddles, and darke ſentences, Written by <hi>A. P.</hi> With a manner of ordering the body for health through euery month of the yeare, and for dieting it for a ſeuen-night after blood-letting. <hi>Written in Latin verſe by</hi> Ioachimus Camerarius.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by Adam Iſlip. 1598.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184116:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="questions_and_answers">
            <pb facs="tcp:184116:2"/>
            <head>Naturall and Morrall Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Anſweres.</head>
            <div type="question">
               <head>WHy hath Nature not giuen a ſting to the king of the Bees, and hath furniſhed all other Bees therewith?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To teach Princes that nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth their dignitie leſſe then tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and that their onely defence ſhould conſiſt in the ſtrength and force of their ſubiects.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is that which oweth moſt, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth leaſt, and of all euils is the worſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Ingratitude, for that monſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth good turnes and payeth venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:3"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What thing in this life is not accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with feare?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A good conſcience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What are pleaſures?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Enemies to chaſtitie, leaders to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, the daughters of diſhoneſtie, and baits of extreame miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What thing is begotten of a mother and anon the mother is begotten by it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Iſe turning to water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> An example of imbecillity, the ſpoile of time, an image of inconſtancy, a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of calamitie, a priſoner to paines, a ſeruant to couetouſneſſe, and finally a food of wormes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> When is fortune moſt to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> When ſhe moſt flatters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What thing is old ere it bee hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A ſecret grudge and malice long conceiued ere it be put in execution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Who beleeue more other mens words then their owne eieſight?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Women, for they giue more credit
<pb facs="tcp:184116:3"/> to them that fainedly call them beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, then to their looking glaſſe that doth gaineſay it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is beautie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A gift of ſmall continuance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What good thing breeds lothſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Plentie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What water is in the ſight of God moſt precious, and in the taſte of men moſt vnſauerous?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The vnfained teares of a penitent ſinner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is it that groweth with the head downeward, and with the root vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> An iſeſickle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is that which moſt deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and moſt deceiueth a woman?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A mans diſsimulation, which hath ſuch a ſweet paſſage through his tongue as it delighteth as the Syren ſongs, and turnes to as deceitfull a concluſion as the Crockadiles teares.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Wherein is couetouſneſſe only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In ſparing and not ill ſpending his time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is it that cheefly ſuſtaineth labour?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hope of reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Who denie their owne requeſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They that demand things impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Who is moſt like vnto a mad man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A drunkard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is that which woundeth the heart, and is worſhipped of the eie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Beautie?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> How ought clemencie to bee mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> So that it breedeth not our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is ſobrietie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The father of good counſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Wherein is a woman moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In her inconſtancie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Of what three things repented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>Cato</hi> done in his life time?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To haue ouerſlipt a day and not to haue encreaſed his knowledge, To haue
<pb facs="tcp:184116:4"/> gone by ſea, where hee might haue gone by land: and thirdly, To haue committed his ſecrets to a woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why ought wee not to diſcloſe our ſecrets vnto women?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they cannot keepe their owne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why are there ſo many that liue diſcontented in wedlocke?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe their firſt loue was groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon luſt, or els in making of their raſh choice they had more regard to the womans dowry then to her conditions, or els the woman reſpected more the mans purſe then his perſonage, or more his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy then his good or ill qualities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why was <hi>Diogenes</hi> called a dog?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe hee did bite indifferently both his foes &amp; his friends, but his friends to their good and amendment, and his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to their ſhame and confuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What men are very daungerous in a Commonwealth?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe that affect nouelties?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What three things are the life and death of life?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Bathes, wine and women, for as the vſe of them is reſtitution, ſo is the abuſe of them life and healths deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is ſtronger then death?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Fame and renowne, and therefore a certaine Philoſopher did call fame the daughter of immortalitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the reaſon that Wine min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with water prouoketh vomit?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe watered Wine hurts the ſtomacke, and weakeneth the retayning vertue or ſtrength of the Wine, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as pure Wine doth ſtrengthen and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doe old folkes neeſe with great difficulty?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe of the weakeneſſe of their nature, and the narrowneſſe of their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why is man more ſubiect to diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and infirmities then any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By reaſon of his intemperancie, and therefore <hi>Schola Salerni</hi> ſayth, <hi>Eſſe cupis ſanus, ſit tibi parca manus.</hi> That is, if thou wilt liue in health, haue a nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly hand, <hi>Ideſt.</hi> Vſe temperance of diet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why doe Phiſitions ſay that it is dangerous to let a fat man blood?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe thoſe that are fat haue leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer veines, and are more hidden and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare not ſo much, moreouer they haue but little blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is the reaſon that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melian chaungeth ſo oftentimes his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By reaſon of his great feare, and becauſe hee maketh much of his blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doe men vſe to lay lime at the foot of a Cherrietree?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To haue ripe Cherries before their ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What man is worthely called bold and couragious?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hee that loues his life, and yet fears not death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the reaſon that ſome die for very ioy, and ſome by too much ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Great ioy doth coole too much the inward and vitall parts of the bodie, and ſorrow and ſadneſſe doth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> choke them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why hath nature made the lungs
<pb facs="tcp:184116:6"/> of all creatures ſpongious, or full of holes, like vnto a ſpunge?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To the end it might receiue the aire the better to coole the heart, and driue away from it all ſuch vapors as are hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why is our heart placed in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the bodie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To quicken equally all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, euen as the ſun giueth light equally to all things being in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the heauens.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why were Iudges in times paſt painted without hands?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To ſignifie thereby that Iuſtice ought not to be corrupted with bribes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is a ſigne of a good Iudge?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If hee departeth from his office with more gaine of good fame then ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> In what ſort ſhould a man ſeek pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the Commonwealth?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As at a fire, which if one ſitteth too neere vnto, doth ſcorch himſelfe, and being too farre off it, ſuſtayneth cold.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What thing maketh a good Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Diſcipline.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What cauſeth deſpaire in a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Beggery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the cheefeſt ſtratagem in warre?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Ripe deliberation, and preſent exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the cheefeſt pollicie in peace?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To feare ciuill diſcord and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent it, and by foreſight to reſiſt forraine inuaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Who are onely to be called reſolute ſouldiours?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe that are determined either to die, or els to obtaine the victory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is a cheefe fault in warre?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Feare of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> How did antiquitie repreſent vnto vs the iſſue of good things?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They made an image holding in the right hand a cup, and in the left hand an eare of corne with a ſprig of Poppy, ſignifying therby that he eaſily is brought
<pb facs="tcp:184116:7"/> aſleepe, that is contented with the fruits of the earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What ſeruice is moſt in requeſt, and being performed, is leaſt conſidered and moſt hated?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Treaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What time is moſt deſired, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained is moſt accuſed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Age.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What men are cheeflie decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe that looke for two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie thinges at one time, namelie for pleaſure and the reward of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is that in the morning goeth vpon foure legges, at noone vpon two, and in the euening vpon three legges?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Man, for in his infancie hee cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vpon hands and feet, in his youth hee goeth ſtraight without any helpe or ſtay, and in his age vſeth beſides his legges the aid of a ſtaffe to ſupport his body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What thing is in the day time as round as a hoope, and at night long as a</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A girdle about a man or womans body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How many waies is violence cheefly committed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Two waies, either by deceit or by force: the one is the practiſe of the Foxe, and the other of the Lyon, and both of them are moſt farre from huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why is vertue had in ſo ſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe ſhee is plaine and cannot diſſemble.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why dooth vertue reiect all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe truth needes no ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What men are moſt ingratefull to themſelues, and leaſt hurtfull to other men.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe that are couetous and enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, for as theſe pine away at other mens welfare and proſperitie, ſo the other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger their ſoules to leaue rich, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps vnthankfull heires behind them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why is heauen ſaid to haue a low gate?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe thoſe that ſhall enter into it muſt firſt ſtoope low and learne humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why did Antiquitie in their chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches place a croſſe vpon the entrance of the quire?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the body of the church did repreſent the church militant vpon earth, and the quire the church trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant in heauen, to teach vs hereby that no man would come from the one into the other vnleſſe hee did ſuffer firſt croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and perſecutions?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is a friend?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Another ſelfeſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is commonly the end of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute life?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A deſperate death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is a cheefe ſigne of a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces clemencie, and a token of his great courage and magnanimitie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To deſpiſe the whiſperings of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull men, and patiently to ſuffer the rage of enuy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Which are the cheefeſt ornaments of women?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Shamefaſtneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> How might a foole reſemble a wiſe man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In hiding of his folly by ſilence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What three things doe men moſt couet?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Riches, Pleaſure, and Honor. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches bee the nurſes of ſinne and iniquity. Pleaſures the guides to calamitie. And Honor the pompe of worldly vanities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why are pleaſures ſo much to bee abandoned?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe their firſt entring is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit and deceitfull, and their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is griefe and repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What thing in this world is alwaies without reſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A guilty conſcience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is it that men moſt doe hunt after, and oftentimes prooueth moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Womens fauor.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is it that women moſt feare, &amp; yet of it do moſt deſire the occaſion?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To be with child they moſt deſire, and fear moſt the hour of their deliuery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What doe children moſt hate, and yet is moſt profitable vnto them?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Correction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is leſſer then a Mouſe, and hath more windowes then a houſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Thymble.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What vice is moſt likeſt to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Tantalus?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hypocriſie, For as the Apples of <hi>Tantalus</hi> ſeemed in ſight moſt beautiful, and yet prooued but ſhadowes: ſo this vice although it beareth a glorious ſhew of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet is nothing els but a meer and a deceitfull illuſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why is it amongſt men now adaies ſo much practiſed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe it is the higheſt degree of diſſembling, and therefore is accounted a ſure ſtep to promotion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What men transforme themſelues into angels of light, and are nothing but Diuels incarnate?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hypocrites.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What men promiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vaine things?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Courtiers, and ſuch as liue in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall hope.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What thing in the latter minute of his age waxeth yong againe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Moone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Who is the mother of all mankind?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The earth, euen by the Oracle of Apollo: for this Oracle being demanded by certaine Princes that were in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie for the kindome of Aegypt, who ſhould ſucceed the late King deceaſed; anſwered, that he ſhould not only be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled King of the kingdome of Aegypt, that firſt ſhould kiſſe his mother, but ſhould likewiſe become monarch of all Aſia. This anſwer being reported by the Prieſt vnto the Princes that were then attending without vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Oracle; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> hauing heard it, ſtept ſuddainly from his horſe and kiſt the ground, ſaying that the earth was the mother of al mankind. The princes that could not deny it made and created him King, who afterward conquered all Aſia, and became quiet monarch of many kingdomes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is it that taketh leaſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in company?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Pride, for it hateth his betters, enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his equals, and deſpiſeth his inferiors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is it that being aliue is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dumbe, and being dead, yeeldeth a moſt ſweet harmonie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Lute, or any kind of inſtrument made of wood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Which is the beſt remedy for things that are not to be recouered?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Obliuion or forgetfulneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is chiefly to be commended in a warrior?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To be in fight terrible, and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt mild.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What ſurfeit is moſt dangerous and leaſt auoided?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſurfeit of ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Who kill their mother ere they be borne, in the reuenge of their father that begot them?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Vipers, for as the male and femall ingender by the mouth, ſo the damme being kindled with luſt in the art of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery, bites of the males head, and the yong ones ere they be borne gnaw their mothers belly open to come forth, and ſo doe kill her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is it that ſooneſt waxeth old?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A benefite, for nothing is ſooner forgotten then a good turne, and nothing longer remembred then an iniury.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What are Vſurers?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Horſeleeches and Caterpillers of the Commonwealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is the leaſt and yet the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitableſt
<pb facs="tcp:184116:10"/> thing in a Garden?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Bee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What wind bloweth no way to profite, and is noyſome to all the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The foiſting of a dogge, the ſmell whereof is noyſome to all the companie that are neere it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Vpon what men are almes deedes worſt beſtowed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Vpon blind men, for they would be glad to ſee him hanged that releeues them. I would not that any man ſhould interprete them in earneſt, which is only written in a merriment, and that for this they ſhould withdraw their charity from ſuch poore men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why do moſt men delight more in fleſh then in fiſh, &amp; why it is more whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer vnto the body?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe it ſtrengthneth more and is of ſounder nouriſhment, or els becauſe it agrees better with the ſubſtance of our bodies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the Law?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A net.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What are the Lawyers?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Burdars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What are the Clients?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Birds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the Court where the Law is pleaded.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The place where the nets are ſpred to take the ſimple and ſilly birds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Whereby doth a womans loue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the ſhadow of our bodies?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Euen as our ſhadow if we runne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it doth fleet away from vs, and if wee runne from it doth follow vs: ſo the loue of a woman, if wee fondly purſue it, will diſdaine vs, but if we ſet light by it or ſeeme to run from it, will moſt earneſtly deſire vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is a chief ſtratageme in war?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Expedition, and not to ouerſlip oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why did the Ancients find fault with <hi>Zeuxis</hi> liberalitie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe he gaue &amp; beſtowed gifts to receiue double againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is the cauſe of greateſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion &amp; the greateſt repleniſher of hel?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Ignorance, which maketh men to worſhip ſtones and diſhonour God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is the greateſt friend to men at libertie, and the moſt enemy to ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:184116:11"/> as are condemned?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hope, which encourageth men at libertie to attempt great matters, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſuch as are condemned vnprepared for death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What ſeaſoneth and ſweetneth the bitterneſſe of warre.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hope of victorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why is fauour bought with mony, moſt vncertaine?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe by diſcontinuance of giuing it breeds inward grudging, and by the ceaſing of liberalitie, it burſteth out into open hatred.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Wherein is an enuious man like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yron?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Euen as yron is conſumed with his owne ruſt, ſo an enuious man pines away by his owne folly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is leaſt to bee reſpected in an Oration?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Gloſing words, for as in coyne the brauery of the ſtampe is little or nothing regarded but onely the weight and the ſubſtance: euen ſo it is no matter how eloquent the Oration be, but how graue and profitable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is an Hyſtory?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A teſtimony of time, a light of veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the maintainance of memory, the ſchoole-miſtreſſe of life, and the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of antiquity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the hardeſt thing to bee learned?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To learne to know himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> How might one eſchew enuy?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By liuing abiect and miſerable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Idleneſſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Father of Lechery, and the highway to pouertie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What are riches?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. Diogenes</hi> called them the vomite of fortune.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What doth caſt from it a greater heat then fire?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Beautie, which ſetteth not only on fire thoſe that touch it, but alſo thoſe that a farre off doe behold it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is death?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The end of trauels, and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is the duty of a wiſe man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To miſtruſt the ignorant, and to know how to skirmiſh with aduerſitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Who is ſometimes a mother and ſometimes a ſtepdame?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Fortune.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What are the moſt precious orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a Citie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The vertues of the Cittizens.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What maketh men conſtant againſt all humane affections?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A good diſpoſition of the mind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why are lawes ſaid to be like vnto ſpiders webs?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they catch ſmall flies, but waſpes and bees flie through them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is the reaſon that for to ſee the better we are wont to ſhut one eie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the other might bee aided with the ſence of the eie which is ſhut and cloſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the cauſe of Hydropſie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The great cold of the liuer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why do thoſe that haue the yellow yandars find hony to be bitter in taſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By reaſon of the great colour wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with their tongue and the palait of their mouth is infected:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why do muske, millions, &amp; cucum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, prouoke vrine?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By reaſon of their great humiditie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the cauſe that old men and women dote?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By reaſon of the great coldneſſe which is in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Wherout doth it proceed that men become pale when they are ſeaſed with feare?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the blood retires to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall parts of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why hath a Scorpion his poyſon in the taile?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the poyſon is his excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why did <hi>Hypocrates</hi> permit thoſe to drinke wine that had a burning ague?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It was for to helpe digeſtion, and to ſtrengthen the parties.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why are the extremities of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more ſubiect to cold then the other parts thereof?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they are not ſo ſolide or ſo well knit together, and are farther remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why do Pullets (their throtes being cut) ſuruiue after it longer then men?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chickens and Pullets haue ſmaller ſinnewes and veines, and therefore life cannot ſo ſoone leaue them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why are men more taller then wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By reaſon of their naturall heat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doe women make water ſtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and men to the contrary?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe their bladder ſtands high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then mens doth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why haue men more teeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they abound more in blood and heat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the reaſon that when mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens breſts begin to grow, they begin to change their voice?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe then the Organs of the voice are wider and leſſer cloſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why are twinnes not ſo ſtrong as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the ſeed which ſhold haue ſerued to one, is parted into two.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doe eager things prouoke ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they drie vp the humours, and conſequently cloſe the ſtomacke faſter vp, which doth cauſe appetite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why doe Lettuce prouoke ſleepe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they engender groſſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why is Iuie alwaies greene?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the heat of it is tempered
<pb facs="tcp:184116:14"/> with humiditie and viſcoſitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why haue Birds no teeth?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the ſubſtance which teeth doe grow of, doth turne into their bils.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> When is vice paſt al hope of remedy?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> When it is growne into a cuſtome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doe matters well executed, pleaſe but few men?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe moſt men are rather gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by affection then by reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is idleneſſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A nurſe of laſciuiouſneſſe and the wel-ſpring of all vices.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What thing metamorphoſeth a man into a beaſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Luſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Which is the higheſt degree of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To make of him a laughing ſtocke beſides, who by our means hath been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Which is the chiefeſt felicitie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To be releaſed of a wicked woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What men are leaſt to be truſted?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe that haue beene diſloiall to their owne country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What thing ſpends moſt prodigally that which couetouſneſſe hath moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly
<pb facs="tcp:184116:14"/> ſcraped together?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Ambition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is a chiefe comfort to the conquered, or to thoſe that are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hope of reuenge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the life of Courtiers?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A continuall hope.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> By what honeſt meanes may poore men encreaſe their ſtocke?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By ſparing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why did the Lacedemonians ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice a Cock when they had obtained vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory againſt their enemies by maine force: and an Oxe when they had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne them by ſubtletie, ſurpriſe, orin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe they preferred Prudence and wit before force or bodily ſtrength, and therefore a certaine captain of Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia was wont to ſay, If a lions skin cannot preuaile, adde vnto it the skin of a foxe, meaning thereby; if force cannot, vſe po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Which are the fruits of pleaſure?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Griefe and repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Which is the firſt ſtep to aduerſitie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The higheſt degree of proſperitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doth men neeſe ſooner being in the ſunne then being neere the fire?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the heat of the ſun doth only diſſolue the humor, and conſumes it not: but the fire doth both diſſolue and conſume it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doe the eies of Cats &amp; wolfes ſhine in the night and not by day?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the greater light doth dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the leſſer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why is the white of an Egge of ſo hard a digeſtion?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By reaſon of the great coldnes of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Why doth Burrage laid in wine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice thoſe that doe eat it?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe it doth encreaſe blood, and ſtrengthneth the heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why did Nature make rather the braine cold then whote?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To temper and moderate the heat of the heart, to the end it might ſerue it in ſtead of a cooler.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What paſsion is that which tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a man moſt and hath leaſt power to ouercome?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A womans inconſtancy, which gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a man, and cannot be ouercome by women themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How ought wee to vſe proſperitie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not to truſt vnto it, for we ought to vſe the gifts of fortune for our neceſsitie, and not to relie vpon them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is pleaſure?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A bait to take men as hookes and nets doe fiſhes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What poyſon ought Princes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid chiefly?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The poyſon of flattery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Que.</hi> What is the reaſon that the bottome of a Kettell being full of boiling water &amp; hanging ouer the fire, is cold notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By reaſon of the hote vapors which continually doe mount vpwards, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the higher parts being warmed, the bottome remains coole for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the water that is vpon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why do thoſe that oftentimes weep piſſe ſeldome?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the humiditie taking his paſſage by the eies dooth eaſe ſo much the more the other parts and members of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why did Nature ordaine neeſing?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To purge the ſuperfluities of the braine, like as the lunges are purged with coffing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What maketh pleaſures moſt ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A rare and ſeldome vſe of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is it that conſumes his mother that bare him, eates his nurſe that feedes him, and then dies, leauing all them blind that ſaw him?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The flambe of a Candle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What men if cauſe do moue them, doe ſooneſt forſweare themſelues?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe that are woont lightly to ſweare without a cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Which is the only phiſick in miſery?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Whereby doth a man pleaſe a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man beſt, and yet diſpleaſe himſelf moſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In giuing her her will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is beſt to bee done for a rich man falling ſicke?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not to make his Phiſition his heire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is Loue?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> An idle bodies paſtime or buſineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How might one auoid loue?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By eſchewing idleneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> How ought we to vſe loue?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As a foole to ſport, or a minſtrell to make vs merry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Who are the beſt creatures vpon earth.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Women next vnto men and Bees.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Who is rich?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He that is contented.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How might one learn to be content?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To vnlearne to couet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What men doe leaſt feare death?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe that feele leaſt comfort in this world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What ought we chiefly to learne in proſperitie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How wee might beſt indure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> Wherein is the life of man like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yron?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Euen as yron if it be vſed doth wear away, and if it be not vſed doth conſume with ruſt: ſo our life if it be neuer ſo well exerciſed dooth decreaſe by time, if not, yet doth it waſt away with idleneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What is the immoderate vſe of too much liberty?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> An occaſion oftentimes of bondage and ſlauery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> What men are moſt vnthankfull?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe that can tell how to receiue a benefit, and not how to requite it, or els thoſe that deny the receit of it, but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe that haue forgotten it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſhadow is moſt deceitfull?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Hypocriſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the chiefeſt reuenue for one that hath no lands?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sparing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> When is clemency moſt hurtfull?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> When rebels are moſt obſtinate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What thing is moſt dangerous, leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoided, and moſt deſired?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The pleaſures of this world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſoile beares both the beſt and the worſt fruit?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The wombe of a woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What ought a ſeruant chiefly to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe to obtaine his maiſters fauor?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Diligence, continuance, and ſecreſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Where is ſilence moſt to be practiſed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In matters of ſecreſie, and amongſt pots and Cannes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> How or what are the gifts of fortune?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Such as are the mindes of thoſe that poſſeſſe them, a help &amp; comfort to them that can vſe them, and a ruine and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw to them that know not how to vſe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What men are moſt vnfortunate in aduerſity?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thoſe that neuer learned to be croſt
<pb facs="tcp:184116:17"/> in proſperity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What feedes a doubtfull life, or him that is by law condemned to die?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Hope of pardon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why were it better to bee among Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, then to liue among flatterers?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe Rauens pray not vpon men but when they are dead, but flatterers deuour them euen when they are aliue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What bitings are moſt ſoreſt and moſt greeuous?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The bitings of neceſsity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What men ought chiefly to bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faults?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thoſe that are alwaies moſt ready to eſpie faults in others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is it to lend money vpon vſury?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To kill a man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why did <hi>Solon</hi> eſtabliſh no law againſt Paricides?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe hee thought that ſuch an enormity could not bee committed by a child, and therefore (becauſe hee ſhould not ſeeme rather to remember men of ſuch a wickedneſſe then to forbid it) would in no wiſe appoint any puniſhment for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What maintaines a Commonwealth?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Reward and puniſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> How ſhould parents take the death of their children?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> As <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> and a lady of Lacena did: for newes being brought to the one, of his ſonnes departure out of this life: anſwered the meſſengers, That he knew long ſince that hee had begotten a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal man. And this lady whoſe conſtancie deſerueth no leſſe praiſe &amp; commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hauing heard that her ſon was ſlaine in the battaile, ſaid to thoſe that firſt brought her the tidings hereof: To that end haue I brought him to the world, that there ſhould not bee wanting one that ſhould doubt and refuſe to ſpend his life and blood in the defence of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherein did <hi>Cyreneus</hi> and <hi>Theodorus</hi> courage and magnanimity moſt chieflie ſhine and appeare?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In his reſolute anſwer to king <hi>Lyſima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> when hee did threaten him with death, for then boldly ſpeaking to the Tyrant, Bid him to feare his Courtiers with theſe bugs, for <hi>Theodorus</hi> is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent (quoth he) whether he rots vnder or aboue the ground.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Who may be ſaid to ſuffer water con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to bee drawne out of his ſpring, and yet for it hath nothing the leſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> He that giueth good counſel to them that demand it, or hee that beſtoweth a benefite vpon another without any hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which may be called a double iniury?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To be defrauded of deſerued praiſes, and purſued with vndeſerued reproches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> By what meanes ſhal one become rich quickly?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In being poore of deſire: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid, If you haue reſpect wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with nature is ſufficed you ſhall neuer be poore, but if you looke vnto that which opinion craueth you ſhall neuer be rich.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What men may be ſaid to liue onely and longeſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thoſe that liue onely and longeſt in eaſe and quiet: And therefore <hi>Adrian</hi> a moſt puiſſant Emperour, who by great trauell and interceſsion obtained licenſe in the end of his daies to dwell in a little village of his, where he liued ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yeares in great reſt and quiet, dying, left an apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant token and teſtimony, that the life
<pb facs="tcp:184116:19"/> led in honor and dignity was not the true life, for he cauſed words to be graued on his tombe, Here lieth the wight whoſe age is of many yeares, but hee liued but only ſeuen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What child is the only heire of a wiſe and worthy Parent?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Hee that inheriteth and is heire vnto all his fathers vertues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is marriage.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A Paradiſe on earth if her lawes bee obſerued, but a hell in the houſe if her ſtatutes be broken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> How many chiefe powers are there of the ſoule?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Three, Intendment, Will, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What three deſerts of the body ſtop the paſſage of theſe three powers of the ſoule?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Ignorance of that which is good, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe of that which is euill, Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and langor of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are the remedies againſt theſe three euils and defects?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Wiſdome, Vertue, &amp; Neceſsity; which to chaſe theſe three euils are thus orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: Wiſdome againſt ignorance: Vertue
<pb facs="tcp:184116:19"/> againſt couetouſneſſe &amp; vice: Neceſsity againſt infirmity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is it that of men is leaſt eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and of God moſt honoured?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Chaſtity, which is precious before God, and a laughing ſtocke before men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is ignorance?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A graue which burieth life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What foure things haue continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence in a Noble mind?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Courage to repell the incroching ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: a heart to conſider a loyall friend: a hand to reward the gifts of the ſimple: and clemency to accept &amp; pardon a well meaning mind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> How many kinds of Sages be there?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Three. The ſage wiſe man, the ſage foole, and the ſage hearbe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherin is a flatterer like vnto a hauke?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe as a Hauke will not come to an empty fiſt, ſo a flatterer to an emptie purſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the firſt ſtep of loue?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The loſſe of libertie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Who after their death, liue in the life of their children?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Such parents as haue brought vp their children, as they may chuſe the good and
<pb facs="tcp:184116:20"/> forſake the euill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Who is alone a worthy and a valiant man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> He who neuer dooth bow his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders at the burden of misfortunes, nor he who neuer panted at his chance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What anſwered <hi>Gorgias</hi> being deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, what manner of diet he vſed that he liued ſo long?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That hee neuer did eat any thing for pleaſure or wantonneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why did <hi>Zenocrates</hi> (aſsigning all the parts of the day to ſome buſines) appoint likewiſe to ſilence his due part?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe he might then priuately diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe with himſelf what maner he ought to keepe in ſpeaking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What did neuer ſpeak wel of any man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Euill will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherein did <hi>Artemiſia</hi> declare her great chaſtitie towards her husband de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In her entire loue towards him, for when her husband <hi>Manſolus</hi> King of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria was dead, ſhee cauſed his heart to bee dried in a veſſell of gold into pouder, and by a little and little drank it all vp ſaying, Their two hearts ſhould neuer depart
<pb facs="tcp:184116:20"/> aſunder: &amp; that ſhe thought there might be no worthier ſepulchre made for it but her owne body. Notwithſtanding ſhee made for his body ſuch a ſepulchre, that for the excellent workemanſhip, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and coſtlineſſe therof, it was taken for one of the meruailes of the world: &amp; for the notable fame of it, all ſumptuous and great ſepulchres were afterwards called Manſalca.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the beſt hauen to him that is penitent?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Confeſsion of his faults, and change of counſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> How might a man become maiſter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer himſelfe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In amending that in himſelfe which he rebuketh in another body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherefore made nature man naked &amp; without weapons to defend himſelfe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Nature hauing beſtowed wiſedome vpon man, hath giuen him means inough to arme himſelfe at his owne pleaſure, as well againſt the cold and heat of the air, as againſt the blowes of his enemy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why are Iudges and Lawyers more honoured of thoſe that goe to law, then Phiſitions are of their patients?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe the gaine of the cauſe doth depend of the Iudge and aduocates: but giuing of health to the patient lieth not in the hands of the Phiſition, but in God only.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why doth a Swanne being neere his death ſing more ſweeter then at any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Nature hath taught this to the bird, to teach vs the good which wee receiue by death, which ſerueth vs for a doom or paſſage to euerlaſting life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why do men ſeeke to auoid pouerty?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe it cauſeth them oftentimes to decline from the right way of vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why doe men drinke water, which notwithſtanding doth not nouriſh?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Water dooth ſpend the digeſtion of the meat through all parts of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why are thoſe that are drunke, cold?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By reaſon of the Wine taken immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, which quencheth and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmeth the natural heat of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doe Phiſitions not miniſter medicines when the ſickneſſe or diſeaſe is at the cheefeſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe they ſhould not oppreſſe or hinder nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the cauſe that children who are moiſt by nature are not bald notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe their humidity is intermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with a temperate heat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why doth Rue being planted vnder a figge tree grow the better, and receiueth more nouriſhment?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe it draws vnto itſelf the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the figge tree, or els the figge tree ſuckes away from the Rue a part of his bitterneſſe, and ſo being ſomwhat ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it groweth the better.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the reaſon why teeth do come againe, and not any other bones of the body?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> All other bones are made and ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of a naturall humor and moiſtneſſe in the mothers wombe: but the teeth are ingendred by a nouriſhing humor, which daily doth increaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the reaſon that when wee ſee others to yawne, we are prouoked to doe the like?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This proceedeth to my iudgement by the vertue of our imagination.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What did moue nature to giue vs ears?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe thereby men might iudge
<pb facs="tcp:184116:22"/> of the difference of ſounds and voices. Through the ears likewiſe is purged the colour which is in the braines, as through the noſe is the flegme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Of what ſtuffe are womens tongues made of?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Of an aſpen leafe, for they neuer leaue wagging.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is moſt praiſed and leaſt practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Honeſty, or els the vertue of libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the firſt ſtep to wiſdome?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To know himſelfe, and the ſecond to feare God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the Magiſtrate?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The mouth of the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is honor?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The reward of vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the property of folly?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To ſee other mens faults and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her owne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the only ſauce of meat?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Hunger, as thirſt is of drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is ſhamefaſtneſſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The tincture and die of vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the cheefeſt pleaſure in this world?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Libertie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> In contracting of marriage what ought firſt to be regarded?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Vertue and not riches: and therefore <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> a woorthy Duke of Grecia being asked why hee had rather to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow his daughter vpon a poor and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, then vpon a rich man ill condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: I (ſaid he) had rather a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money, then money wanting a man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> How might one beſt learn to diſcerne a knaue?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In comparing him by an honeſt man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What ought a wiſe man to practiſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> How to accomodate himſelfe to the time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is a chiefe cauſe of our owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Selfeloue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Whom chiefely hurteth pouertie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Him that cannot carry it patiently.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the ſauce of labor?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Who liues moſt ſafely?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Hee that doth not diſcouer his owne ſecrets.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the ſtate of a rich churle, or of a couetous man?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A continuall torment, &amp; by extream deſire of gaine, accompanied with a fear to looſe thar which he hath gotten.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What thing gets friends?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Proſperity, but aduerſity tries them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why ought we in requiting of a good turne, imitate the earth?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe it giues more then it recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why ought we not to blame, nor like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to praiſe our ſelues?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe the one is a ſigne of folly, and the other a token of inconſtancy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are riches?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Nets to intrap men, and thornes to pierce the heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the ſureſt guard of a Prince?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The loue of his ſubiects.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What two things do chiefly bridle and encourage men?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Reward and puniſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why haue wiſe men alwaies hated an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe it is a ſpice and kind of folly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherein is warre better then peace?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Warre ſtirreth vp the minds of men to vertue, and peace drawes them to idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and laſciuiouſneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:23"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why doe old men die almoſt without paine?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By reaſon that all their ſences are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitated and weakened.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why doth ſorrow and grief make men to looke old before their time?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe they dry vp the moiſtneſſe of the body, and age is nothing but a kind of drineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why muſt Wheaten bread chiefly be ſalted and leauened?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe that Wheat by nature is ſop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and very, and ſalt doth dry the great of it, and the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen makes it more lighter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why are fat things not ſubiect ſo ſoon to corruption?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe they participate ſo much of the aire and the fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why is a Diamond not ſo ſoon burned by thy fire as any other precious ſtone?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By reaſon of his ſoliditie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why dooth oyle ſwim aboue any kind of liquor?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe of his fatneſſe, and all fat things doe much participate of the ayre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the reaſon that ſome men are more able to endure longer then other?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe ſome of them are more cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke and ſome more flegmaticke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the reaſon that when wee are a hungred, our ſpitting is more ſalter then otherwiſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe hunger encreaſeth choler, which eaſily becommeth bitter by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his ſharpeneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why are women commonly more fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then men?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe they are more colder of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, and doe leſſe exerciſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the cauſe that the milk of pale or white women is not ſo wholeſome as that of them that are browne?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Blacke women are more whoter of nature, and therfore by conſequent their milke is better digeſted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Of what conditions is man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Of all conditions of foules &amp; beaſts that God hath created. Bold as a lyon, ſportful as an ape, dumbe as a fiſh, prating as a parret, filthy as aſwine, neat as a ſwanne, ſwift as a hart, ſlow as a ſnaile, prowd as a peacocke, gentle as a lambe, chaſt as a turtle, loyall as a horſe, feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as a hare, ignorant as an aſſe, ſubtle as a ſerpent, angry as a waſpe, and lecherous
<pb facs="tcp:184116:24"/> as a Moonky.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Of what mettall are womens tongues made of?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Of <hi>Virgils</hi> braſen flaile, which ſtrooke both friends and foes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What difference is there betweene a ſcold and a harlot?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> As there is betweene the Viper and the Crockadile, for the ſcold with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage deſtroieth her husband, &amp; the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot with diſſembling loue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is that which is coldeſt clad in freeſe, and warmeſt attired in precious ſtones?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Pride, which hath no grace but in brauery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is life without literature?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A mans graue, or an image of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What wicked mother hath brought forth a good child the onely prop &amp; ſtay of all gouernements?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Ill manners haue brought forth good lawes, to the eſtabliſhment of vertue, and the ſubuerſion of vice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What ought we to thinke of the time which we haue here?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That wee haue little ynough &amp; looſe much.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Where ought marriage not to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Where loue cannot be compelled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which are the titles and epithets of the ſunne?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To be parent of the day, gouernor of the world, a quickner of the body, the eie of the firmament, the heart of nature, the king of the ſtarres, and the viſible ſonne of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which are the wings of time?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Time paſt, preſent, and to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which are the teeth wherwith time conſumes all things?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The night, the day, life and death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the cauſe that in our age there are not ſo many excellent men, as there were in times paſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By reaſon of nature which daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, or becauſe vertue is not ſo much eſteemed of now adaies as it was in times paſt, or els it is the cuſtome of all ages to complaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is anger?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A ſhort madneſſe, or els the beginning of fooliſhneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is vertue?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A ſweet harmony of nature, to the
<pb facs="tcp:184116:25"/> found and time wherof al good men giue an eare vnto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What difference is there between wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and a ready wit?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The wiſe man giueth good counſell, and the witty man preſently conceiues and iudges of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What priuiledge haue braue and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious knights aboue other men?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not to be ſubiect nor to be daunted by fortune.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſhadoweth nay darkeneth the great vertues in <hi>Philip,</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, his ſonne?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Drunkenneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is Wine immoderately taken?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The blood of the earth turned to poyſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is Wine moderately taken?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A whetſtone to memory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why did the Aegyptians ordaine that commonieſters and plaiers ſhould beare no witneſſe in any cauſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe ſuch kind of people are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly giuen to wickedneſſe, and for a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle ready to do a miſchiefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is nobilitie without vertue?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A bladder puft vp with pride and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which are the vertues that doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct vs to heauen?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Faith, hope, charity, pietie, religion, and godlineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the poyſon of friendſhip?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Flattery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What kind of ignorance is moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not to know God, and then not to know himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherefore is vertue ſo amiable?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe ſhee is alwaies conformable to reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What warre is lawfull?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That which is conducted to obtaine peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherefore is the firſt counſel of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which ſhe giueth without thinking on it, far better then that which ſhe hath ſtudied vpon?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Euen as all vnreaſonable creatures are by inſtinct of nature driuen to their actions: ſo a woman although ſhe be ill, yet the intelligence which nature hath giuen her, which will not bee deceiued, nor abuſe any body, compels her by the firſt motion to good: But if ſhe gets lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to vſe her owne nature, all that ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:184116:26"/> ſhall doe will be naught.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherefore are women commonly more couetous then men?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe they know they ſhould bee no body without riches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherefore are thoſe that haue great heads more giuen to ſleepe then thoſe that haue little heads?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The greater the thing is the more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pors it doth containe, and humiditie doth cauſe ſleepe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why are lentiles and cabages ſo ill for the eie ſight?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By reaſon of the melancholike blood which they engender.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the cauſe that many die with too much ioy?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe the vitall ſpirits abandon the heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherefore ought we not to faſt long?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By reaſon that by too much faſting a maſſe of ill humours is ingendred, and prouoke vomit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the cauſe that we haue better ſtomackes to our meate when the wind is at the North, then at other times?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By reaſon of his coldnes which knits together and holds within vs the natural
<pb facs="tcp:184116:27"/> heat of our bodies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the reaſon that Vineger is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wholeſome to thoſe that are chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, &amp; is of contrary operation to thoſe that are melancholicke?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe it aſſwageth choler by his coldneſſe, and dries vp melancholie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the reaſon that in tract of time Wine becommeth more whote?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe the aquoſity thereof euapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and vaniſheth away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the cauſe that ſome wines ſower ſo lightly?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe that in the time of Vintage the grape was full of ſuperfluous humors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why dooth the wild Bore vſe to piſſe before he runnes away?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To vnlade him of the burden of his water for to runne the ſwifter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> When is it nothing diſcommendable to exceed the meane?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> When it is vſed to exerciſe and driue drowſineſſe out of ſluggards.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds do not loue their wiues?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thoſe that loue their bodies &amp; their goods, and not their mindes and good conditions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is chiefly to bee regarded in a witneſſe?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> His honeſty, as in a Lawier eloquence and good vtterance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why can yoong men hardly keepe a meane?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By reaſon of the natural heat aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> How might a foole ſeeme and bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted wiſe?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> If he goes braue in attire and ſpeakes little.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the reaſon that ſome haue hard and ſome haue ſoft heare?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The greatneſſe and ſmalneſſe of the Pores is cauſe of it, for ſoft hear co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by reaſon of the ſmalneſſe of them, and hard heare for the contrarie. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore women haue commonly ſofter hear the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men, becauſe their naturall cold doth reſtrain and cloſe the Pores.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the reaſon that Garlicke and Onyons doe bud although they are not in the earth?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe of their great abundance of moiſtneſſe and heat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why is a dead body heauier then that which hath life within?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A body aliue is full of ayre and fire which doe hold it vpright, for their
<pb facs="tcp:184116:28"/> nature is alwaies to mount vpwards, and a dead body is nothing but a lumpe of earth, whoſe nature is heauie and alwaies tending downewards.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What dooth preuent an occaſion of murmuring?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Equalitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why doe vices ſhaddow themſelues vnder the colour of vertues?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe if they ſhould come in their own ſhape, but few would giue them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why ought Parents to bee very curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in ſeeking of good tutors and maſters for to inſtruct their children?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe as their Parents are the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their bodies, ſo the maiſters are the fathers of their ſoules: and as childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe imitate the nature of thoſe that haue begotten them; ſo out of their maiſters maners as out of a nurſes breſt, they ſucke their vertues and vices, their good and ill conditions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is it that in louing too much tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to mortall hatred?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Ielouſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Who murdereth the liuing &amp; the ſame of the dead?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A Slanderer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherin is our enemy commonly bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto vs then our friend?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe our enemy ſpeares not to tel vs our faults, which friends ſeeke for the moſt part to hide from vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is as ſeldome found as the Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix of Arabia?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A truſty friend.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is it that Kings cannot conquer?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Mens affections.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> In what place is flattery a Iewell?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Where diſſembling ſwaies the ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What ought wee in this life moſt to remember, and leaſt to feare?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The houre of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is mans life?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A thing more brickell then glaſſe, more lighter then the ſmoke, and ſwifter then the wind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What garment is the beſt?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That which couers malice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are dice?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Fortunes whelpes, which conſume a mans wealth, and empaire his patience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are womens vowes?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Words written in the wind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are their promiſſes?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Carracters figured in the ayre, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures grauen in the ſnow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is a beautifull ſtrumpet?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> An Adamant that drawes, &amp; a Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that with her painted skin doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure men, and he that ſurfets with it, drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth deadly poyſon and ſo doth periſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are womens lookes?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Kalends, that can determine no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Of what nature and condition is a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Of the nature of quickſiluer, for as this mettal whereſoeuer it meeteth with gold it mingleth with it: ſo wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they chiefly reſpect in a man his wealth, and alwaies will they priſe gold for beautie or for any other internall or externall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which are the two only means to win womens fauour?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sweet words and high praiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What men are in one of the higheſt degrees of miſerie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> Thoſe that are wiſe by their own woes, and thoſe can make a right anatomy of miſery by their owne diſtreſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is a bad woman?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A painted continent of flattery, of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, of inconſtancy, and the very guide that leads men vnto the pernicious laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth of endleſſe miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are womens curteſies?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sharpe ſhowers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Who ſlew the fourth part of the world?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Cain</hi> ſlaying his brother <hi>Abel.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What flower is in ſight moſt beautifull, in ſmell moſt ſauerous, and in operation moſt deadly?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The pleaſures of this world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The image of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is a woman?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The ſimilitude of man, and a cabinet of much good and euill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is a yong man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A burning candle ſoone perceiued and quickly quenched.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is more ſwifter then the wind?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A mans thought.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is mote ſwifter then the thought of a man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Time, for it tarrieth for nothing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is ſeldome ſeene and neuer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Deſtinie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which is the chiefeſt touchſtone to try a mans friend and his owne patience?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Aduerſitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What vices did darken <hi>Marcus Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> his great liberalitie and patience in aduerſitie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Dicing, drunkenneſſe, gluttony, and too much familiarity with his domeſtike ſeruants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are the effects of Poetry?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Spurres and enticements to vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why did the Romans forbid the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Wine to women?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe it doth prouoke them to luſt, and doth altogether extinguiſh reaſon in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What ought a ſeruant chiefly to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe for to gaine his maiſters fauour?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Diligence, continuance and ſecreſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Who killeth a man friendly?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A flatterer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſoile beares both the beſt and the worſt fruit?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The wombe of a woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why are Angels painted with wings?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To ſignifie their quickneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What might men doe to be beleeued?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Wet their tongues on their hearts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What difference is there betweene loue and friendſhip?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> As much as there is betweene beauty and vertue, ſubſtance and ſhadowes, for when aduerſities flow then loue dooth ebbe, but friendſhip ſtandeth alwaies faſt in euery ſtorme and tempeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What pleaſure is chiefly bought with repentance?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The loue of a ſtrumpet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are the diſcommodities atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon trauellers?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To bee forced to fit their humour to euery place and perſon, to beare many mens braues or feele the force of their weapon, to bee oft in danger of theeues, many times of wild beaſtes, and euer of flatterers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why did the Caldies whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would ſet forth the picture of a Gentleman, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe him with his hands alwaies open?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To ſignifie that liberality was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impreaſe of a Gentleman, and that to giue was alwaies heroicall: and therfore <hi>Titus</hi> Emperour of Rome was woont to ſay: Giue, if thou wilt bee worthy the worlds Monarchy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What things are moſt welcome, moſt ſweet, and beſt liked of?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Inexpected chaunces, loſſes recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and things ſeldome ſeene.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Wherevnto may flatterers bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To trencher flies, that attend more vpon a man for hope of gain then for any perfite loue. To doues that flock chiefly where the houſe is faireſt. To emptie veſſels that haue lowd ſounds, and haue nothing within but wind. To painted ſheaths that haue ruſtie blades. To glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious flowers that haue no ſmell: becauſe they pretend much friendſhip, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine nothing but ſuperficiall flattery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is Loue?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A paſsion full of Martyrdome, Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Griefe and Diſcontent, hauing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures but tempered with paines, &amp; a ſhort delight mixed with a long repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is beauty?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A fading flower, to day fit for the eie, and to morrow withered and to bee caſt into the graue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why did the ancients in old time paſt miſlike of thoſe that wiſhed and deſired to be moſt happy and fortunate?</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe that too much fortune bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth forgetfulneſſe, a contempt of God and of all godlineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> For what cauſe were women being met at Rome in the ſtreetes by any of their kindred, kiſſed by them?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> For to know if they had drunken wine, for it was forbidden vnto them to drink any, as it appeareth by one <hi>Egnatius</hi> that ſlew his wife, becauſe ſhe had drunk a cup of wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What was the reaſon that king <hi>Ageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> would neuer ſuffer his picture to be drawne or ſhadowed?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe his onely intent was to leaue after him his deedes to ſerue in ſteed of his picture, and ſo rather to repreſent the perfections of the mind, then the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal lineaments of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What are open praiſes?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Secret flatteries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Which are the three chiefeſt vertues of a ſouldior?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Prudence, Fortitude, and Liberalitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is Wiſdome?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A diuine influence infuſed into the minds of men, which keepeth them from committing that wherevnto they are
<pb facs="tcp:184116:32"/> forced by ſenſuall appetite.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Why is vertue placed by equal propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene two vices?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe that the mean which is kept betweene two extreames, is that laudible action which by no other name can bee tearmed but by the title of Vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What maketh men in earth famous, in their graues glorious, and in the heauens immortall?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is prodigalitie?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A fire of the mind, which is ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient in heat, as it ceaſeth not while any matter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>buſtible is preſent to burne neceſſary things to duſt and cinders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Who is only to be accounted a valiant man?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> He that without any furious or raſh reſolution feareth not to hazard himſelf in the greateſt perils whatſoeuer, for the welfare of his countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is the greateſt preiudice that may happen vnto a Commonwealth?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To be gouerned by an vnwiſe prince.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="riddles">
            <pb facs="tcp:184116:32"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Diuers pretty Riddles with darke ſentences.</head>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vdge of me by perfect skill,</l>
                  <l>My youth reſtord by caſting bill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>An Eagle.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>When I am old I caſt my skinne,</l>
                  <l>Whereby I doe come yong againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A Snaile.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>What Iudge on the earth did giue,</l>
                  <l>The greateſt ſentence when hee did liue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pilate</hi> when hee pronounced ſentence
<pb facs="tcp:184116:33"/> of condemnation againſt Chriſt Ieſus.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>White I am and blacke withall,</l>
                  <l>I haue eies and yet am blind,</l>
                  <l>Gaine and loſſe not without brall</l>
                  <l>I doe procure, as you ſhall find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Dice.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>I wound the heart and pleaſe the eye,</l>
                  <l>Tell me what I am by and by.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Beautie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>I am within as white as ſnow,</l>
                  <l>Without as greene as hearbes that grow,</l>
                  <l>I am higher then a houſe,</l>
                  <l>And yet leſſer then a mouſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A Walnut hanging on the tree.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>A mayd there was that married a man,</l>
                  <l>By whom were many children gotten,</l>
                  <l>Yet all them died and went away,</l>
                  <l>Before their mother was begotten.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:33"/>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It was <hi>Eue</hi> and her children who all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ere ſhe was begotten, for ſhe was neither borne nor begotten, but created.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What mother a child doth beget</l>
                  <l>And ſhe of it is gotten againe,</l>
                  <l>Which although ſtrange it ſeemes to be,</l>
                  <l>Yet it is true I tell thee plaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Water turning to Iſe, and Iſe again tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to water.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Tis blacke without and blacke within,</l>
                  <l>And hath foure corners as I win.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A drie Turfe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oedipus</hi> that whilom haſt reſolued a greater doubt,</l>
                  <l>Vnfold this Riddle vnto mee which now I ſhall put out.</l>
                  <l>When I did liue then was I dumbe, &amp; yeeld no harmony,</l>
                  <l>But being dead I doe affoord moſt pleaſant melody.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:34"/>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Any muſicall inſtrument that is made of wood.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Yet once againe I meane to prooue thy skill but in a ieſt,</l>
                  <l>Which if thou doeſt reſolue to mee thou ſetſt my mind at reſt:</l>
                  <l>Whether was man created firſt before the beard, or els</l>
                  <l>The beard before the man, that ſhew, and thou ſhalt win the bels.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>All creatures created were before man in their kind,</l>
                  <l>And ſo was eke the bearded goat as wee in bookes doe find.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>In at the window when I looke</l>
                  <l>(Beat not your braine long about this)</l>
                  <l>Then in the houſe about I go,</l>
                  <l>Now tell me quickly what it is.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>The ſhining of the ſunne.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>She ſet her backe againſt the wall</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:34"/>
                  <l>And tooke vp petticote ſmocke and all,</l>
                  <l>There came a yong man with a gin,</l>
                  <l>And put it in a handfull in.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A ſhoemaker put a new paire of ſhoes on a womans foot.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>There dwell foure ſiſters neere this towne,</l>
                  <l>In fauour like and like in gowne</l>
                  <l>When they runne for a prize to win</l>
                  <l>All at once they doe begin</l>
                  <l>One runs as faſt as doth the other</l>
                  <l>Yet cannot ouertake ech other.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>The foure wings of a Windmill.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>When it through the wood doth goe</l>
                  <l>It toucheth euery twigge below.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is the Snow.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>When it doth goe through the wood,</l>
                  <l>It toucheth neuer a twigge forſooth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A penny in a mans purſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:35"/>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>I lay in bed and woe I was,</l>
                  <l>So did my wife but worſe ſhe was,</l>
                  <l>She bid me riſe and put it in,</l>
                  <l>And thus we were both well againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A man with his wife lying in bed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heard ſome theeues about their houſe, wherevpon both being afeared, the good wife praied her husband to riſe and ſparre the dore.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What is it that moſt nooſes hath,</l>
                  <l>Within the houſe made of a plate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>The hangers where the pothookes hangs vpon.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>I am foule to be lookd vnto,</l>
                  <l>Yet many ſeeke me for to win,</l>
                  <l>Not for my beautie nor my skin,</l>
                  <l>But for my wealth and force to know:</l>
                  <l>Hard is my meat whereby I liue,</l>
                  <l>Yet I bring men to daintie fare,</l>
                  <l>If I were not, then ale knights ſhould</l>
                  <l>To ſing this ſong not be ſo bold,</l>
                  <l>Nutmegs, Ginger, Sinamon and Cloues,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:35"/>
                  <l>They gaue vs this iolly red noſe,</l>
                  <l>The fourth parts of the earth I ſhow</l>
                  <l>The time and howers as they doe goe.</l>
                  <l>As needfull am I to mankind,</l>
                  <l>As any thing that they can find.</l>
                  <l>Many doe take me for their guide,</l>
                  <l>Who otherwiſe ſhould runne aſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is the loadſtone, for without it no Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot were able to guide a ſhip in the Occean ſeas.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>I am a cheefe ſtrength of the land</l>
                  <l>When vpon foure pillers I ſtand</l>
                  <l>And if theſe foure ſhould faile indeed</l>
                  <l>Then ſhould I find two more at need,</l>
                  <l>Foure lights I haue to be my guide,</l>
                  <l>And the fiſt ſhall not ſtand aſide,</l>
                  <l>For tis more brighter then the ſunne,</l>
                  <l>And doth remaine when life is done,</l>
                  <l>And though one corpes two heads dooth weare,</l>
                  <l>No monſter yet is it I ſweare.</l>
                  <l>Vnknit this knot, and tell to me,</l>
                  <l>At leiſure ſir what I might be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A horſeman being a horſebacke, who hath foure eies with thoſe of his horſe: and firſt is his reaſonable ſoule, whereby he is
<pb facs="tcp:184116:36"/> chiefly guided nor is not ſubiect vnto death.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Sixe Hares did run within a plaine,</l>
                  <l>whom hounds had ſtarted out the neſt:</l>
                  <l>Hill vp, hill downe, they ran amaine</l>
                  <l>till they were weary, and then did reſt.</l>
                  <l>They caught them once and ſcapd againe</l>
                  <l>more eager went they then before.</l>
                  <l>And tooke more paines then (as I win)</l>
                  <l>to bare away the game and more.</l>
                  <l>The hounds and hunters all were one,</l>
                  <l>ech lik'd his game and tooke his pray</l>
                  <l>But when the ſport was paſt and done</l>
                  <l>they left the Hares, and came away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a match at bowles played in a bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alley.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Ten mens length, and tenne mens ſtrength, and ten men cannot rayre it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A cable or rope which tenne men cannot breake by force.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Aman I was, man I am</l>
                  <l>But yet as tame as any lam.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:36"/>
                  <l>Though I am blind the way I ſhew,</l>
                  <l>Which all men that ſee me muſt goe.</l>
                  <l>And to put your mind out of doubt,</l>
                  <l>Eight legges I haue that beare about</l>
                  <l>My burden, more then any hath</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe he be in my eſtate.</l>
                  <l>In time therefore doe learne of mee,</l>
                  <l>As I before haue done of thee.</l>
                  <l>If he had knowne that brought our woe</l>
                  <l>Ventred had not vpon his foe,</l>
                  <l>But for his fault we ſubiect bee</l>
                  <l>To this eſtate where you ſee me,</l>
                  <l>I am that which you leaſt deſire,</l>
                  <l>But yet that you ſhould moſt require,</l>
                  <l>Geſſe what I am good fit, therefore</l>
                  <l>Before you doe knocke at my dore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a dead man and thoſe foure that do carry him to his graue, with <hi>Adam</hi> our firſt parent who brought death into the world.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>It ſwallowes raw fleſh ſtones and all</l>
                  <l>And in the middeſt it hath a toong,</l>
                  <l>Which neuer ſpake ill of old or yoong.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a Hauke that takes his ſtones for to caſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:37"/>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Ouer a hole two ſtones there lie,</l>
                  <l>Stiffe it went in, limber comes our,</l>
                  <l>Beloued it is of women all</l>
                  <l>And of our neighbours here about.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is corne that comes of the mill.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Sharpe are my clothes as any pin,</l>
                  <l>be not raſh therefore me to win.</l>
                  <l>But bring me naked to thy mill,</l>
                  <l>and then with me thy mind fulfill.</l>
                  <l>And though ſweet thou findſt me to be,</l>
                  <l>yet ſurfeit not ſir vpon me.</l>
                  <l>But for a change vſe me ſomewhile,</l>
                  <l>ſo ſhalt thou not thy loue beguile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a Cheſſenut, and by the mill is ment the mouth.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>In open field I cannot lie,</l>
                  <l>And yet I may reſt quietly,</l>
                  <l>Within a boxe of luory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a feather in a windy day.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:37"/>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Stiffe ſtanding, ruffe hanging</l>
                  <l>Betweene a maids legs</l>
                  <l>In a froſtie morning.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a diſtaffe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>I am as little as any nit,</l>
                  <l>And ſerues the king at euery bit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Salt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Who weares his end about his middle</l>
                  <l>Once in his time, tell me this Riddle.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A theefe whoſe armes are tied with the halter wherewith he ſhall be executed.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>My fleſh and skin is red,</l>
                  <l>But white is all my heart,</l>
                  <l>Where round about a wall is ſet,</l>
                  <l>Beaten with euery dart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a Cherry and a cherriſtone.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:38"/>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Yonder is it, and here I haue it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A mans breath, or any other liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What wight is he that many doth feed</l>
                  <l>And yet himſelfe doth die for need</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A preacher inſtructing others, and doth quite contrarie to his owne doctrine, and by theſe meanes ſtarueth his ſoule.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Tell me ſir whom I might be,</l>
                  <l>a father I had, but mother none,</l>
                  <l>Yet many a mother haue had of me,</l>
                  <l>who all to earth with me are gone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Our firſt parent <hi>Eue</hi> who had no mother, and no other father then God almighty.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What is moſt likeſt to a horſe</l>
                  <l>(Beſides a Mare he meanes)</l>
                  <l>That feedeth vpon hay and graſſe,</l>
                  <l>Vpon Peaſe, vpon Beanes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:38"/>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A Gelding.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>My husband giues two gownes to me</l>
                  <l>of ſundry colours euery yeare,</l>
                  <l>Greene is the one, which I doe weare</l>
                  <l>So long till it be all thredbare,</l>
                  <l>White is the other as the Swan,</l>
                  <l>of many peeces vp and downe,</l>
                  <l>Yet like to that few workmen can</l>
                  <l>deuiſe to make another gowne.</l>
                  <l>The wiſer ſort (wherein they dote)</l>
                  <l>doe call mee foole vpon a toy,</l>
                  <l>But yet of me they take a note</l>
                  <l>That death is paſt when I doe ioy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a Mulbery tree, greene in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and white with Snow in the Winter, who in Latine is called <hi>Morus,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies in Greek a foole. This tree is of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that it will not caſt any buds before all other trees haue, whereby wee certainely know when ſhe begins to bud that the cold and Winter is altogether paſt for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſeaſon.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>A ſhip there driues vpon the tide,</l>
                  <l>that ſailes doe beare, ſhe hath no maſts,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:39"/>
                  <l>But one oare ſhe hath of ech ſide,</l>
                  <l>her ſailes the ſnow in whiteneſſe paſſe.</l>
                  <l>In her front weares too lanternes bright</l>
                  <l>but when ſhe is vpon point to fall</l>
                  <l>Then lend an eare, for great delight</l>
                  <l>of muſicke ſhe affords to all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a Swanne, who being neer her death ſings moſt ſweetly, as authors doe record.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>God ſpeed wife, and good ſpeed dame,</l>
                  <l>Shall I put my rough rombello in your rough hame,</l>
                  <l>Put him in, and clap to the gate</l>
                  <l>For new ſhauen it was of late.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A horſe put into a new mowen meddow.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Round I am, yet cannot reſt,</l>
                  <l>When I am ſpited of the beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A Tennis ball when two good players play together.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What man is he of wit ſo baſe</l>
                  <l>That weares both his eies in a caſe</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:39"/>
                  <l>For feare of hurting them it is,</l>
                  <l>And I doe find it not amiſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is he that cannot well ſee without ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles, and doth carry them about him in a caſe for feare of breaking them.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>My prey I ſeeke the fields and woods about</l>
                  <l>&amp; haue more teeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſt within the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</l>
                  <l>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer my graue I haue found out,</l>
                  <l>then ſafe I bring it to my maiſters hand,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my backe the deare he laies</l>
                  <l>and there doth kill one, ſometime more,</l>
                  <l>He ſhuts me vp and goes his waies,</l>
                  <l>Better contented then before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a combe and a louſe killed vpon the backe of it.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>A tree there is that boughes doth beare</l>
                  <l>in number fiue as I doe know,</l>
                  <l>Of equall length they neuer were,</l>
                  <l>and on their tops doe hornes grow,</l>
                  <l>Yet they are tied about with gold</l>
                  <l>except the longeſt without doubt,</l>
                  <l>Which for vſe ſake might be controld,</l>
                  <l>if it with gold were hoopt about.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:40"/>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is ones hand &amp; his fingers that are full of golden rings, the middlemoſt excepted, becauſe a ring doth not fit that finger.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>I was Not, I am Not, and ſhall Not bee,</l>
                  <l>yet I do walke as men may ſee,</l>
                  <l>I runne and ſpeake to get a fee</l>
                  <l>though I am not in my degree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a man whoſe ſirname was maſter Not.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Deaffe I am and cannot heare,</l>
                  <l>and when I worke I feele no paine,</l>
                  <l>Some doe curſe me, ſome ſpeake me faire</l>
                  <l>though well they know it is in vaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Dice and dicers.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What bloody Tyrant was that wight,</l>
                  <l>That with a murthring blow</l>
                  <l>The fourth part of the earth did ſlay:</l>
                  <l>Which thou canſt tell I trow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cain</hi> in ſlaying of his brother <hi>Abell.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:40"/>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>In what place of the earth</l>
                  <l>dooth the skie ſeeme to bee</l>
                  <l>No larger then a yard or twaine,</l>
                  <l>which I pray tell to mee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>In the bottome of a well.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>A thing that I take that I looſe,</l>
                  <l>yet nothing to my woe,</l>
                  <l>And that I take not, that I keepe,</l>
                  <l>yet would it faine forgoe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>He that is louſie, all thoſe lice which hee takes throwes them away, and thoſe that he cannot take keepes them ſtill, and yet would faine be rid of them.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What thing is onely vpon this earth not ſubiect vnto feare,</l>
                  <l>Nor doth not waigh the threatnings of Tyrants, pinne or haire?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A good conſcience.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:41"/>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What doth with his root vpwards grow,</l>
                  <l>And downwards with his head doth ſhow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>An iſeſickle.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What is leſſer then a Mouſe,</l>
                  <l>And hath more windowes then a houſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A ſpider in the middeſt of his web, or els a thymbell.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Belly to belly</l>
                  <l>Hand vpon backe,</l>
                  <l>I put a raw morſell</l>
                  <l>In a gaping gap.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A mother or nurſe that giues ſucke vnto her child.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>I doe walke yet doe not goe,</l>
                  <l>I doe drinke yet no thirſt ſlake,</l>
                  <l>I doe eat yet doe not feed,</l>
                  <l>I doe worke yet no worke make.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a man that dreams, who in his dream ſeemes to doe all theſe things, yet in deed doth none of them.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:41"/>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>As bitter as gall,</l>
                  <l>As ſweet as milke,</l>
                  <l>As high as a hale, and hard withall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A Walnut vpon the tree.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>I am nor fiſh, nor fleſh, nor voice,</l>
                  <l>Yet when I am borne I make a noiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A fart, or els the thunder.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>When we by the way doe goe,</l>
                  <l>Vpon our ſhoulders we beare our way</l>
                  <l>If wee were not then many ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Wet to the skin in a rainy day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Maſons, Tylers, and men of ſuch like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation, carrying ladders vpon their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to build and tile houſes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>M.</hi> and <hi>I.</hi> did make great mone,</l>
                  <l>When C. vpon C. was left alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:42"/>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> made great mone,</l>
                  <l>When Chriſt vpon the croſſe was left alone.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>When I to the wood doe goe,</l>
                  <l>Then my head homewards I doe ſhow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>An axe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>In me and in my ſhining light.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a burning candle.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>In the laſt minute of mine age</l>
                  <l>I doe waxe young againe,</l>
                  <l>And haue ſo ſtill continued,</l>
                  <l>ſince world did firſt beginne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is the Moone.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>I doe owe moſt yet nothing doe I pay,</l>
                  <l>Euill I am, and the worſt I ſay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Ingratitude, which monſter receiueth good turnes and paieth vengeance.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:42"/>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>What men are thoſe that backwards gaine,</l>
                  <l>Their ſmall liuing, not without paine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>Gardeners and Ropemakers.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Old I am ere I am borne</l>
                  <l>And when I am hatched, take heed of mee,</l>
                  <l>Or els thou maieſt ſoone be forlorne</l>
                  <l>If thou doeſt nothing looke to thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>The grudge of a ſecret enemie long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in mind ere it is put in execution.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>What is it that God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to be done,</l>
                  <l>was not done, and yet God was well pleaſed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>The ſacrificing of <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>My belly to thy ſide I lay,</l>
                  <l>And the hole is a ſporting when we play.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a Bagpipe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:43"/>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Hitty pitty within the wall,</l>
                  <l>And hitty pitty without the wall,</l>
                  <l>If you touch hitty pitty (my ioy)</l>
                  <l>Hitty pitty will bite the boy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a nettle.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Clincke clancke vnder a bancke,</l>
                  <l>Tenne aboue foure and neere the flancke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A maid milking of a Cow.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Trip trap in a gap,</l>
                  <l>As many feet as a hundred ſheepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is the haile when it fals.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Red within and red without,</l>
                  <l>It is as ruffe as a Beares ſnout.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A ſtrawbery.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>A wicked father did beget</l>
                  <l>A daughter fit vnto his hand.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:43"/>
                  <l>But ſuch good children ſhe did get</l>
                  <l>That are the props of euery land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>The deuill begot ſinne, and ſin procured good lawes which are the ſtaies of all go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernements.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>God ſpeed faire ladies by one and by one,</l>
                  <l>I am ſent I cannot tell to whom,</l>
                  <l>And I doe bring I cannot tell what,</l>
                  <l>I count her wiſe that tels me that.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A louer ſent to his loue a meſſenger to put her in mind of her promiſe as to come vnto him, and ſhe ſent backe this anſwer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</l>
                  <l>Tell thy maiſter in my name</l>
                  <l>Wheen trees are turnd and wels be dry</l>
                  <l>And dead vpon quicke then come will I.</l>
                  <l>Meaning at midnight, when the fire brands ſhould be turned vpwards, and the pots ſhould bee empty, and the fire raked vp with the cold aſhes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe would come.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>I went and I could not tell whether,</l>
                  <l>I met and I wot not with whom,</l>
                  <l>He gaue me that I ſhall neuer forget,</l>
                  <l>And yet I came a maiden home.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:44"/>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A child that went to chriſtening.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>I haue a ſmith without a hand</l>
                  <l>He workes the worke that no man can</l>
                  <l>He ſerues our God and doth man eaſe</l>
                  <l>Without any fire in his furnace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a Bee that makes honny and waxe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Foule is my fault that feeds me full,</l>
                  <l>To gorge on mothers bowels ſtill,</l>
                  <l>I went abroad to ſeeke my fire,</l>
                  <l>And my wiues ſonne I doe deſire</l>
                  <l>Such a one the man muſt be</l>
                  <l>As is the ſonne of wife to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ioſeph</hi> went to ſeeke Chriſt, when hee found in the Temple Preachers amongſt thoſe of the Synagogue.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>What is it that in the morning</l>
                  <l>vpon foure legs doth goe,</l>
                  <l>And about noone it ſtandeth faſt</l>
                  <l>vpon two and no moe:</l>
               </lg>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:44"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>I make all blind as did delight.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>I am cald by the name of man,</l>
                  <l>yet am as little as the mouſe,</l>
                  <l>When Winter comes I loue to be</l>
                  <l>with my red gorget neere the houſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A Bird called Robin red breſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>Although my bodie little is,</l>
                  <l>yet I doe pleaſe the hearers eare</l>
                  <l>If I were tame it were not amiſſe,</l>
                  <l>Then I ſhould liue in leſſer feare.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>The Nightingale.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What is it that more eies doth weare</l>
                  <l>then fortie men within the land,</l>
                  <l>Which gliſter as the chriſtall cleare,</l>
                  <l>againſt the ſunne when they doe ſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A Peacockes taile.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>When I goe to the water ſide</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:45"/>
                  <l>at home my heart I leaue behind,</l>
                  <l>Tell me what I am without pride,</l>
                  <l>if it by any meanes you find.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a pillowbeare.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>My head is round, my bodie ſmall,</l>
                  <l>And I hold that, that ſauours all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A Salt ſeller and Salt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>Head and eie I am only,</l>
                  <l>What I may be now tell to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A button of copper or of any mettall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>A Bird vpon a houſe I ſaw,</l>
                  <l>ſixe legs it had, yet but one taile,</l>
                  <l>Two heads beſides more then a daw</l>
                  <l>name me this Bird and win the ale.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A hearnſhaw had taken a frog &amp; brought it to her yong ones in the neſt made vpon the top of a houſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:45"/>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>All my body belly is</l>
                  <l>And leſſer then it my mouth is not</l>
                  <l>I doe containe that makes men mad</l>
                  <l>What I am ſir now tell me that.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A malt ſack full of malt wherwith ſtrong drinke is brued.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>My belly is bigger then all the reſt</l>
                  <l>Wherein men vſe to put the beſt,</l>
                  <l>Broad is my foot, ſhort is my necke,</l>
                  <l>If ill ye vſe me then feare a checke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A bottle of glaſſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Question.</head>
                  <l>My coat is greene and I can prate,</l>
                  <l>Of diuers things about my grate,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a priſon I am ſet</l>
                  <l>That hath more loopholes then a net.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A Parret in a cage of wyar.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>I doe aſſemble many wight,</l>
                  <l>Yet I keepe me out of their ſight,</l>
                  <l>And doe not come once where they be,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:46"/>
                  <l>Yet euery day they may ſee me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>A bell touling to a ſermon.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="riddle">
               <lg>
                  <head>Queſtion.</head>
                  <l>What mill is it that hath two wings</l>
                  <l>which flie about without the wind</l>
                  <l>A greaſie miller lookes to all things</l>
                  <l>whiles it doth turne and doth not grind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>Solution.</head>
                  <l>It is a iacke, and the greaſie miller is the cooke.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="anecdotes">
            <pb facs="tcp:184116:46"/>
            <head>Worthy ſayings and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die anſweres, compyled into one booke out of ſundrie Chronicles, by <hi>A. P.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="account">
               <head>A very fit and fine compariſon made by a Gentleman of Genua.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Odowicks force</hi> willing to exact a great and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney vpon the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the city of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nua. His embaſſadour was bid by one of the cheefeſt of the citty to dinner, and a little before dinner as they were walking in the garden together, and the Cittizen eſpying the hearbe Baſil ſaid vnto the Embaſſador: Runne ſoftly my Lord with your hand ouer this hearbe, and then ſmell vnto it, which
<pb facs="tcp:184116:47"/> hee did, confeſsing it to haue a moſt ſweet and comfortable ſauor. Now my lord (quoth the Cittizen) ſtraine and bruſe this hearbe in your hand and then ſmell vnto it, which hee did, affirming it to haue a noiſome and foule ſmell. Wherevpon the Cittizen ſaid vnto him, my lord, if the Duke <hi>Lodowick</hi> runneth ſoftly with the hand of his power and authoritie ouer this citty without either force or violence, he ſhall find her of a good ſmell and wonderfull obedient, but if hee doth oppoſe himſelfe againſt her and dooth ſtraine and force her, ſhee will yeeld him a ſower and a hard taſt and ſauour by diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and rebellion. The humanitie of Princes maketh obedient and tractable Cittizens.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The anſwere of</hi> Iouian Pontanus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IOuian Pontanus</hi> a very excellent Poet &amp; Philoſopher being demaunded vpon a time wherefore he did eat but of one diſh at meales, and of that yet very ſoberly: anſwered, To the end I ſhould haue no need of the Phiſition.</p>
               <p>All Phiſitions affirme that the diuerſity of
<pb facs="tcp:184116:47"/> meats hindereth digeſtion, and breedeth diſeaſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>A compariſon made by a Spaniard.</head>
               <p>THe lord <hi>Gonſalues</hi> playing at dice and being a great looſer, perceiued his ſon <hi>Alexander</hi> to be greeued at it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he ſaid vnto certain Gentlemen there preſent, The Hyſtories record that <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great being a child did weepe when he heard that <hi>Philip</hi> his father had obtained the victory of a battell, and beſides had conquered a kingdome all at once: And being demanded wherefore hee wept, anſwered that hee feared that his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would winne ſo many realms and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries that hee ſhould leaue him none for to conquer. And quite contrarie (quoth the lord <hi>Gonſalues)</hi> is it with my ſonne <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> now readie to weepe for my croſſe lucke and great loſſes, becauſe hee feareth that I ſhall looſe ſo much that I ſhall leaue him nothing for to looſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:48"/>
               <head>A pretty quippe giuen vnto two Cardinals by a Painter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RAphell Vrbin</hi> being a very excellent and skilfull Painter, vpon a time hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring two Cardinals (with whome hee was very familiar) to reprooue and find fault (only for to anger him) with a certaine pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paule,</hi> which hee had very artificially painted and finiſhed, ſaying that the pictures faces were too high colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and too red, without further ſtudying gaue them this anſwere: My lords maruaile not hereat, for I haue purpoſely ſo painted them as they are now in heauen, and not as they were here vpon earth, for this redneſſe commeth vnto them bluſhing euen for very ſhame to ſee the church ſo ill gouerned by ſuch and ſuch like as your lordſhips.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>The anſwere which the great Turke gaue to the Embaſſadours of the King of Hungarie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BAiazet</hi> Emperor of the Turkes, inuading with a great army Bulgary a part of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,
<pb facs="tcp:184116:48"/> The king <hi>Sigiſmondus</hi> ſent his embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors vnto him to deſire him not to moleſt &amp; trouble his ſubiects and countrie, wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by no law he had not any right claime or title. <hi>Baiazet</hi> to anſwere herevpon, cauſed great ſtore of armours and other warlike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to be brought into a certaine hall appointed for that purpoſe, and hauing ſent for the Kings Embaſſadors, ſaid vnto them: Loe here (my lords, pointing with his finger vpon the armours) the titles whereby I doe claime, and am to poſſeſſe the crowne and kingdome of Hungarie.</p>
               <p>Right and equitie haue no place in the court of a Tyrant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>A pleaſant reproouing of the Marques of Mantua.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRederick</hi> Marqueſſe of Mantua, as he did ſit at dinner among many Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, one of them hauing almoſt made an end of his porrige, ſupt vp the reſt, and to excuſe his inciuilitie craued pardon of the companie. The Marqueſſe in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of them all gaue him this ready an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, ſir, aske pardon of the Swine, for vnto
<pb facs="tcp:184116:49"/> vs you haue done no offence or iniury.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>A worthy deed of an Italian knight.</head>
               <p>AN Italian knight as hee was ſitting at dinner, ſaw two Gentlemen that had alwaies behaued themſelues moſt valiantly in the warres and had done good ſeruice to their countrie, to ſtand as abiects of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, becauſe all places were taken before: wherevpon he did riſe, and ſo cauſed all the reſt to riſe with him for to make place vnto theſe two Gentlemen, ſaying: Giue place vnto theſe two Gentlemen for to eat their meat, for if they had not beene with vs in ſuch a fight (naming the place) wee ſhould at this time haue had nothing for to eat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The tyrannicall ſentence of</hi> Proſpero Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonna.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRoſpero Colonna</hi> Collonell of the Italian infanterie within the Garriſon of Milan, a Cittizen of the twon came vnto him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining againſt the exactions ſpoiles and forceable robberies of his ſouldiours, vnto
<pb facs="tcp:184116:49"/> whom hee gaue this anſwere: Mylan is like vnto a Gooſe, for the more he is pulled the fairer will be his feathers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of Pope</hi> Sixtus <hi>the fourth and a Frier.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>POpe <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth hauing beene a Frier of S. <hi>Francis</hi> order, and being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced to the Papall dignitie, was viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon a certaine time by a Frier of his Order, who had been one of his chiefeſt friends and familiars: the Pope willing to ſhew him ſome priuate fauour, brought him into his cabinet, wherein he had a very rich treaſure, and ſmiling ſaid vnto the poor Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Now <hi>Frater,</hi> I cannot ſay that which S. <hi>Peter</hi> my predeceſſor ſaid: <hi>Aurum nec argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum habeo,</hi> I haue neither gold nor ſiluer. It is moſt true (quoth the Frier) but holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you cannot ſay likewiſe as he ſaid to the impotent, creple and lame, <hi>Surgite &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulate,</hi> Ariſe and walke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The wiſe ſaying of</hi> Charles <hi>the fift Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NEwes being brought vnto the Emperor as he ſat in counſell, that the Marques
<pb facs="tcp:184116:50"/> of Guaſſa was with all his forces diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fited by the Frenchmen, Cardinall <hi>Grandelle</hi> his Chancellor, fearing that the affaires of the Realme ſhould ſucceed the worſe for it, ſaid to the Emperour: Sacred Maieſtie, this ill reencountre is to be kept ſecret. Wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Emperour anſwered, It is not poſsible to keepe things cloſe done before ſo manie witneſſes, but that which is yet to bee done and attempted, is not to be reuealed.</p>
               <p>It is very daungerous to a Realme when the enemie knoweth the ſecrets as ſoone as they are determined.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the humilitie of</hi> Godefrey <hi>Duke of Buillon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen the Duke <hi>Godefrey</hi> of Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon with conſent of all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes was choſen king of Ieruſalem, and therevpon the royall crowne was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and preſented vnto him, he did refuſe it, ſaying: It is not meet for mee a Chriſtian Prince to weare a crowne of gold, whereas Chriſt King of Kings did weare but one of thornes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The laſt will of</hi> Saladin <hi>King of Aſia.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAladin</hi> King of Aſia, Syria, and Aegypt, declared vpon his death bed how miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable hee knew the nature and ſtate of man to bee: and therefore commanded that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead they ſhould cauſe his ſhert to bee carried vpon a launce through all his camp, and inſight of all the lords, captaines, and ſouldiors of his army, and hee that ſhould carrie it ſhould crie with a lowd voice, <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din</hi> ſubduer and vanquiſher of all Aſia a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all his riches which hee hath gotten and conquered, carrieth nothing with him but this only linnen.</p>
               <p>The greateſt triumphs of man in parting out of this world, are the workes of charitie and godlineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The wiſe anſweres of</hi> Antonius Panor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus <hi>to King</hi> Alphonſus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANtonius Panormus</hi> being demaunded of the King what was moſt neceſſary and requiſit vnto them that would liue together peaceablie in the ſtate of marriage, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:184116:51"/> that moſt commonly as the Poet ſayth:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Semper habet lites alternaque ſurgia lectus </l>
                  <l>Inqua nupta iacet,</l>
               </q>
               <p>that is,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>With quietneſſe is ſeldome bleſt,</l>
                  <l>The bed wherein a wife doth reſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Anſwered, that there were two thinges moſt requiſite: The firſt, that the husband were deaffe, for not to heare all the follies, ſcolding wordes, and ill reports of his wiues diſordered life: The ſecond, that the wife were blind, for not to ſee the great enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and exceſsiue intemperance of her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of King</hi> Lewys <hi>of Fraunce and a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>KIng <hi>Lewys</hi> in his wars againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror being on a time in one of his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels ſomewhat far from any of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, a certaine Germane knight thinking to make himſelfe rich by the preſent opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie, ſurpriſed the king vnawares, &amp; ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:184116:51"/> his Maieſties horſe by the bridle, cried out with a loud voice, The king is taken. The king full of courage and magnanimitie drew his courtelax, and gaue the poor ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour ſuch a blow that he fel dead vpon the ground; and then ſaid, Now you may ſee bold and aduenterous knight that at cheſſe the king was neuer taken alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Of the ſaid King and the Chauncellor of Bourgony.</head>
               <p>THe ſaid king <hi>Lewys</hi> hauing heard that the Duke of Bourgony his Chauncel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, being a very rich and wealthy man, had founded and erected in his countrey a verie ſumptuous and a coſtly hoſpitall aſwell in building as in moouables, ſaid that it was more then reaſon that the Chauncellour of Bourgonie (who had in his life time made many poore men) ſhould at the end of his daies build an Hoſpitall for to lodge and to releeue them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſubtill anſwere of</hi> Edward <hi>King of England vnto</hi> Iohn <hi>King of France.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DVring the truce which was betweene <hi>Edward</hi> King of England, and <hi>Iohn</hi> King of France, the Engliſhmen by compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and a great ſumme of money took the caſtle and the towne of Guines, wherevpon King <hi>Iohn</hi> complained, ſaying that the King of England had broken the truce of peace ſo ſolemnly confirmed by oth, and had done contrarie to the contract thereof. The King of England gaue him this anſwere, I haue not (quoth he) broken the leaſt point of the contract, for in it is neuer an article contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whereby it is forbidden to trafficke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, &amp; to exerciſe the truce of marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe one with another.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Touching a benefice.</head>
               <p>A Certaine Eccleſiaſticall man hauing but one benefice, railed and inneighed moſt ſharply alwaies againſt thoſe that were Non reſidents. It came to paſſe by tract
<pb facs="tcp:184116:52"/> of time that hee happened to ioine one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice to another, and as he was for it repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by ſome of his friendes, who oftentimes had heard him ſpeake and preach againſt it, and had knowne him alwaies to be of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie opinion: gaue them this anſwere, I craue pardon for it ſirs for it was but for want of ſight, for hee that hath but one eie ſeeth not ſo cleare as he that hath two. My bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice which I had firſt was but one eie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I did ſee, but now hauing two eies I perceiue things more apparent then before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The words of Pope</hi> Iulius <hi>as touching the exerciſe of warres.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Pope was a man that loued wars, which purpoſely hee nouriſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene kings and Princes, and as vpon a time ſome of his friendes did ſay vnto him, Holy Father, many noblemen find it verie ſtrange to ſee you to maintaine warres and ciuill broiles, ſeeing the eſtate where God hath called you vnto ſhould bee a place of peace and quietneſſe, ſaying that you do car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the keyes to that end for to ſhut out all
<pb facs="tcp:184116:53"/> diſcord and diſſention, and to let in all bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly vnitie, whereas now they accuſe you to doe the contrary. Herevpon he anſwered and ſaid, Thoſe that haue ſpoken hereof vnto you, know not what they ſay: Haue yee not alwaies heard that S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paule</hi> were companions (and in very deed they had but one church) my predeceſſors haue alwaies vſed S. <hi>Peters</hi> keies, but I will aid mee with the ſword of Saint <hi>Paule.</hi> One amongſt them replied herevpon and ſaid, you know holy Father that our Lord ſaid vnto S. <hi>Peter,</hi> Put vp thy ſword into his ſheath: It is true (quoth the Pope) but it was after the blow was giuen.</p>
               <p>By theſe words he declared that he was Martiall altogether.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Of King Alphonſus and his ieſter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALphonſus</hi> King of Naples, had in his court a certaine ieſter who was wont to write in a booke all ſuch follies which in his iudgement ſeemed wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be noted, which ſuch as were courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers did oftentimes commit. It happened that the King himſelfe had occaſion to ſend a
<pb facs="tcp:184116:53"/> Blackamoore whom he had had long about him, into the Eaſt countries with ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Duckets for to buy horſes. The ieaſter according to his ordinarie vſe did enregiſter this act likewiſe among his other writings, as if he had accounted it but a meere point of follie. Not long after the King called for his booke, becauſe it was long ſince his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty had read in it, and as hee was peruſing euerie thing, found at laſt the hyſtorie of himſelfe, of his Blackamoore, &amp; of the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand duckets in it. The king being herewith offended, asked of his ieſter to what end he had put this in his booke, or what occaſion had mooued him ſo to doe: Becauſe, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he, your Maieſtie hath not done wiſely in my ſimple iudgement to truſt your mony with a ſtranger, whome perhaps you are like to ſee no more. But if hee returneth (quoth the king) and bringeth with him the horſes, what wilt thou ſay then to it? Wilt thou then further accuſe me of folly? When hee ſhall be returned, anſwered the ieſter herevpon, I will blot your name out of my booke, and will put in his inſteed of it, for then he ſhall prooue a greater foole then your maieſtie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:54"/>
               <head>Of the Archbiſhop of Colen and a laborer.</head>
               <p>A Certain labourer as he ſaw vpon a time the Archbiſhop of Colen riding all in armes, and accompanied with a great troupe of ſouldiors, did heartely laugh at it. Herevpon being demaunded why hee did laugh, anſwered ſimply that hee did laugh, maruelling that S. <hi>Peter</hi> Chriſts vicar being himſelfe verie poore had left his ſucceſſors thus rich and wealthy, and were rather ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with Souldiours and Courtiers then churchmen. The Archbiſhop willing to inſtruct him better in this point, told him that he was a Duke by birth and an Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop by calling, and that hee at that preſent as Duke went thus in armes and guarded with ſouldiours, but when hee had occaſion to be in the church, that then hee vſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as a Biſhop. My lord (quoth the labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, I would to God then you would tell me that if the Dukes grace ſhould happen to fall to the deuils ſhare, what ſhould then become of my lord the Archbiſhop?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:54"/>
               <head>The ſentence of the Duke of Britane.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohn</hi> the eight Duke of Britane willing to marry his ſon <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> vnto <hi>Iſabell</hi> daughter to the king of Scotland: the yong Prince inquired what ſhe was for a lady, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere was made him that ſhe was a very fair Damoſell, well fauoured, comely of bodie, and well diſpoſed for to beare children, but that ſhee wanted vtterance. Shee is ſuch a one as I deſire quoth the yong Duke: for I account a woman wiſe inough when ſhe can make a difference betweene her husbands ſhert and his doublet, and knoweth his bed from another mans.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The anſwere which Empreſſe</hi> Barbara <hi>late wife to</hi> Sigiſmundus <hi>Emperor gaue to thoſe that gaue her counſell to remaine a widdow.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter the Emperor <hi>Sigiſmundus</hi> deceaſe, madame <hi>Barbara</hi> his late wife was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled by ſome of her familiers to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in that bleſſed eſtate and to remaine a widdow, immitating the example of the
<pb facs="tcp:184116:55"/> Turtledoue, which after the death of her mate coupleth no more with any of her kind, but keepeth a perpetuall chaſtity. Herevpon the Empreſſe anſwered, If you counſell me to imitate and follow the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and nature of the birds, in whom there is no reaſon, why doe you not as wel alledge vnto mee the example of the Pigeons and Sparrowes which are birds in their kind, as well as of the Turtledoue?</p>
               <p>Euen as the Turtledoue after the death of her mate doth couple no more with any other of her kind, euen ſo the Pigeon and the Sparrow are alwaies in loue indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the birds of their nature and feather.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>The auncient ceremony which was vſed in the creation and annointing of Kings.</head>
               <p>VVHen any King was crowned in times paſt (which was commonlie in that place where his predeceſſours were buried) the Biſhop that ſhould annoint and inſtall him, carried before him in his left hand a ſmall bundle of tow, and in his right hand a burning torch or waxen candle, and
<pb facs="tcp:184116:55"/> as he was putting the fire vnto the flaxe, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his face towards the king, and ſaid vnto him with a loud voice. <hi>Sic tranſit gloria mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> So the pompe &amp; glory of the world doth vaniſh away, which he repeated three times.</p>
               <p>It was for to ioine humilitie to authoritie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The anſwere which the Earle</hi> Lazaram <hi>gaue to the Tartarian Embaſſadors.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe king of Tartary willing to inuade with a great power the kingdome of Hungarie, ſent his embaſſadors to the court of <hi>Lazaram</hi> with a Mule laden with a ſacke full of corne, to demand of him free and quiet paſſage through his countrie, ſo to enter into the kingdome of Hungary. The embaſſadors performing their commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, found the Earle vpon one of his caſtels called Archforme: and being well informed of their charge, demaunded of him free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for their lord and his army with ſuch due and faithful obedience as it became vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: their lord and king was elſe determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſend into his territories more Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours then there were grains of corne within
<pb facs="tcp:184116:56"/> the ſacke that was vpon the Mules backe, and therewith they ſcattered the corn ouer all the court of the caſtle. The Earle hauing heard them with patience, gaue them like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a moſt bountifull entertainement, and appointing to giue them anſwere the third day, cauſed in the meane time to be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a great ſtore of Cockes, Hens, and Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, and to bee ſhut vp for his purpoſe three daies without meat, which being immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed by his ſeruants, at the time expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the Duke cauſed all theſe foules to bee brought into the court of his caſtell in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the ſaid Embaſſadors, which in leſſe then half an houre had pickt vp all the corn thus ſcattered by the Tartarians. Herevpon the ſaid Earle ſaid to the Embaſſadours, Tel to your lord in my name, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the great number of his men, yet ſhall hee nor bee able to ſet out ſo manie as ſhall ſuffice to ouercome and conquer vs, as you haue ſeene by the ſimilitude of my Chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins. God alſo gaue to the Earle the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The anſwere which</hi> Eraſmus <hi>of Roterdam ſent to king</hi> Francis.</head>
               <p>KIng <hi>Francis</hi> hauing earneſtly ſollicited by ſome of his embaſſadors, that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and renowned perſonage <hi>Eraſmus</hi> of Roterdam, that it would pleaſe him to come into France, and receiue of him the beſt entertainement which he were able to giue him: for this king did account it one of his cheefeſt felicities to haue diuers learned men about him. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſent his Maieſtie this anſwere, Learned men (my ſoueraine) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble faire tapiſtries, which the further they ſtand remooued from the eie, the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and perfecter they ſeeme to bee, but if they are viewed and regarded neer by, they looſe much of their former grace, beauty &amp; perfection. And therfore (my ſoueraign) par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me if I had rather to remain your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruant in theſe parts where I am, in ſuch reputation with your maieſtie as I am alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, then neerer vnto your highneſſe in leſſe fauour and eſtimation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:57"/>
               <head>A most Chriſtian act done by the Earle of Anion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOokes</hi> the fift of that name Earle of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, as hee had wonne a great battell againſt his enemies neere the towne of Sees, his Souldiours had taken a great number of priſoners, whom they had bound, chained, and had lodged them within the church. The Earle in the morning willing to hear ſeruice, and ſeeing ſo many priſoners within the church, wonderfully diſpleaſed with it, turned his face towards his ſouldiors ſaying vnto them, My fellow-ſouldiors and friends, what haue you done, do ye not know that the church is the houſe of God and a place of praiers &amp; of liberty? And you haue made it a priſon, and a den of thraldome; wherein you haue beene very much ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene: and herevpon cauſed all the priſoners to bee looſed and ſet at libertie, and hauing giuen them meate and drinke ſent them all away without paying any ranſome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Paſquill of</hi> Leo <hi>the tenth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PAſquil is an old piller of ſtone ſtanding in the market place of Rome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon euery firſt day of the year called New-years day, euery man faſteneth (cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly notwithſtanding) many ſcrols, libels, and writings, in praiſe and diſpraiſe of Princes &amp; great potentates. It happened that in Pope <hi>Leos</hi> daies the tenth of that name, there was ſet vpon this piller a white paper wherein theſe ſeuen letters ſtood written.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>M. C. C. C. C. L. X.</head>
               <p>THe Pope being very deſirous to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ſignification hereof, and knowing that euery man would interprete them by vertue of the letters numerable, 1460, being the date of a time paſt alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and knowing that theſe letters ſhould haue ſome other ſignification and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, cauſed a diligent inquiry to bee made for to find him out that had ſet vp this ſcrol, and with much adoe the partie being found
<pb facs="tcp:184116:58"/> out at laſt and brought before the Pope, &amp; earneſtly demaunded and examined vpon the interpretation of thoſe letters, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to declare &amp; expound them vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that his holineſſe would vouchſafe to pardon him and neuer to trouble or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt him for it. This being promiſed, hee ſaid vnto the Pope: Holy Father, theſe ſeuen letters will be thus interpreted.</p>
               <q>Multi Cardinales Caeci, Creauerunt Caecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Leonem, Decimum.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>A worthy act of</hi> Galatius <hi>Duke of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT was told to <hi>Galatius</hi> that there was in Milan a very craftie and ſubtill Lawier for inuenting of means to prolong cauſes, and to make them neuer ended whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he had vndertaken to doe it either for fauour or els for money. The Duke deſirous to trie his skill, inquired of one of his ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards if there were nothing due to any that furniſhed his houſe with prouiſion and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries. The books of account being peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, there was found a hundreth pounds to
<pb facs="tcp:184116:58"/> be due to the Baker. Hereupon the Duke cauſed the poore man to repare before the Senate, and addreſsing himſelfe to this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate, demanded counſell of him for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying the payment of this money. The Lawyer promiſed the Duke that he would find meanes and law that the Baker ſhould finger no part of that mony in a whole year, or els in two, if it ſeemed good vnto him. The cauſe being debated and ready to bee iudged, the Duke himſelfe demaunded of the Lawyer if it were poſsible to find ſome further remedy to delay the payment of the ſaid ſumme. To whome the crafty Lawyer anſwered, that the cauſe ſhould not bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded yet in two years. O wonderfull iniuſtice (quoth the Duke) and man full of iniquitie? Knoweſt thou not that I owe the man this mony? Wilt thou againſt my conſcience &amp; thine owne wilfully fruſtrate the poore of their right, and of that which is due vnto them? Shall a man go to law for that which he oweth, Take this villaine hence, ſaid he, vnto his men, and let him preſently be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted without further iudgement, and let his body be quartered, to the end that other may take example by his fall to beware of
<pb facs="tcp:184116:59"/> the like, and that hereafter the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth be no more corrupted by him. This ſentence with the full conſent of the Senat was preſently executed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>The great charity of a Duke of Sauoy.</head>
               <p>A Certaine Duke of Sauoy being asked by the embaſſadors of the king of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, where his Gray-hounds were which he fed for the chaſe, and moreouer that it would pleaſe him to let them haue a view of them: The Duke did deferre it till the next day, ſaying, that if they would the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the paines to come vnto him, they ſhould haue a ſight thereof. The next day as they came at the time appointed, hee brought them into a great and large hall, where a great number of poor people were eating and drinking at a long table. Behold now, quoth the Duke to the Embaſſadours, the Gray-hounds which I feed, wherewith I pretend to chaſe and to take (next that which my Sauior hath purchaſed for vs all) the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and life euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>The workes of charitie are of ſo great force that the Scripture in euery place doth
<pb facs="tcp:184116:59"/> moſt earneſtly commend them vnto vs, with ſuch an aſſurance of reward, that a cup of cold water ſhall not bee giuen for Gods ſake without a tenfold recompence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>The pleaſant anſwere of a Gentleman.</head>
               <p>A Young Gentleman whoſe mother was lately deceaſed, did mourn for her, and being ſeene vpon a certaine time in the kings court mounted a horſe backe with his foot-cloth of crymſon veluet, the ladies &amp; other damoſels of the court laughed him to ſcorn, ſaying, that they found it very ſtrange to ſee his horſe deckt with a foote-cloth of red veluet, whereas he himſelfe did mourne for the death of his Mother. My ladies (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Gentleman herevpon) you haue herein ſome reaſon, but yet ye ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider likewiſe that the mother of my horſe is not yet dead as that he ſhould mourne for her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of Cardinall</hi> Coſſa <hi>that made himſelfe Pope by force.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Cardinals being aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the citty of Bologne vpon the election of a new Pope immediately after the deceaſe of Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> Cardinall <hi>Baltaſar Coſſa</hi> (biſhop of the ſaid place) came alſo there in counſel accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with a great number of ſouldiors, ſaying to all the Cardinals there preſent, if they did not chuſe a Pope according to his mind and liking, that hee would make them all to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent it. The whole aſſembly being aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at theſe threatnings, and ſeeing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſouldiors about the counſel houſe, named diuers vnto him, but none did like orcontent him. Herevpon as they were all taken with a great feare, willed him to name one him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and if he were fit for the place, they ſaid that they would accept of him. <hi>Coſſa</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon called for the Papall cope for to put it vpon him whome he would haue choſen, which as it was brought, took it, and caſting it ouer his owne ſhoulders ſaid, <hi>Ego ſum Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa.</hi> The Cardinals although it was an act
<pb facs="tcp:184116:60"/> againſt cuſtome, were notwithſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to conſent to this extraordinary ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and called him Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth.</p>
               <p>Ambition in all eſtates cauſeth great troubles, and bringeth the miniſtery in great contempt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of a requeſt preſented to king</hi> Alphonſus.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe king <hi>Alphonſus</hi> was knowne to bee a Prince delighting greatly in the hearing and ſaying of wordes well and readily ſpoken. A certaine man of baſe degree and ſomwhar needy, addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the king, ſaying, My ſoueraigne doe iuſtice vnto me and giue me the law, I haue a creditour to whome my father now lately deceaſed did owe a debt, my father left me nothing wherewith to pay him, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding vpon his earneſt ſute I made ſhift to pay it him, and hee ſo inſtantly demaunded the ſame againe afterward of me, that I was forced to pay him the ſame debt againe: He yet not contented herewith, did moleſt me afterward againe for the ſame debt, and yet at this preſent ſues me moſt vehemently for
<pb facs="tcp:184116:61"/> it. I haue left nothing wherewith I ſhould pay him, and if your grace dooth not aſsiſt me in this extremity, I ſhall bee vndone for euer. Truly (quoth the king) this is an vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and a moſt cruell creditor, What is he for one? My liege (anſwered the poore man) it is my belly, to whome I haue payed the debt ſo long and ſo oftentimes, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is remained wherwith to content him any more, theſe are therefore humbly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your grace to aſsiſt me in my wants, &amp; to helpe me for to giue him his due. I haue ſuch another creditor (ſaid the king:) your grace ſpeaketh moſt true anſwered the poor man, but God be thanked you haue alwaies ynough wherewith to pay him, and not I. The King hearing this requeſt ſo well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, commanded a peece of mony to be giuen him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>King</hi> Lewis <hi>ſayings touching thoſe that had benefices and offices.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEe was wont to ſay that aſſes had for the moſt part better daies and liued more at hearts eaſe then horſes did, for horſes (quoth he) run in poſt to Rome for
<pb facs="tcp:184116:61"/> prebends and benefices, whereof many aſſes are already prouided.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of king</hi> Alphonſus.</head>
               <p>THis king as hee heard vpon a time that a certaine king of Spain had ſaid that literature was not greatly to bee required in a Prince, anſwered, That this was bellowed as an oxe, and not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as a king: and that they were not the words of a man, but of a crowned aſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>Of the ſame king, and one begging another mans office.</head>
               <p>A Certaine officer of his hauing with an amorous potion loſt his wits, one of the Courtiers did beg for his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and liuing, as if it were vnmeet that his place ware ſupplied by a mad man. It were a moſt vngodly deed (anſwered the king) to take the ſubſtance and liuing from him whom God hath barred from all meanes to get and gather any more hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:62"/>
               <head>The last will and Teſtament of a Lawyer.</head>
               <p>A Certaine Lawyer hauing in his life time gathered together great riches, &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no kindred to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he might bequeath his wealth, as he lay vpon his death bed, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed all his goods to bee employed in the building of an hoſpitall, wherein no other diſeaſed perſons ſhould bee receiued but ſuch as were mad and lunaticke, and allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery man a large and ample portion to their mainteinance, willed that vpon both the gates of the hoſpitall this poeſie ſhould be ingraued in golden letters, <hi>Of mad men I got it, to mad men I leaue it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The counſell which</hi> Coſme de medicis <hi>gaue to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine officer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine man as hee had gotten an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice not far from Florence by the mean of <hi>Coſme de medicis,</hi> demaunded
<pb facs="tcp:184116:62"/> and asked counſell of the ſaid Lord how he were beſt to behaue himſelfe in his place for to keepe himſelfe in authoritie. The lord <hi>Coſme</hi> gaue him this anſwere, Apparrell thy ſelfe richly, and ſpeake little.</p>
               <p>He that ſpeaketh little cannot be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of folly, and braue attire encreaſeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>A bold anſwer which a captain gaue to king</hi> Charles <hi>the ſeuenth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certaine Captaine being ſent from the campe to <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeuenth, King of France, for to ſhew vnto him the whole eſtate of the Army, and that for want of victuals, money and other neceſſaries of warre, the Frenchmen had loſt ſome holds, townes and battels, againſt the Engliſhmen. The king willing to vſe ſome priuate familiarity with him, ſhewed him all his daintie fare, delicious prouiſions and furniture, all his paſtimes, his ladies and ſumptuous banquets, and all other ſuch like things wherein he tooke his cheefeſt recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and felicity. And as hee demaunded how it did like him, the Captaine boldly &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:184116:63"/> without feare gaue him this bold and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute anſwere, My ſoueraigne (quoth hee) I neuer ſaw Prince that loſt his owne more pleaſanter then your Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>He is very blind that ſporteth when the roofe of his houſe is on fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſaying of Pope</hi> Vrban <hi>the fift of that name.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHarles</hi> king of Fraunce willing to void his Realme of all outlandiſh and forrain ſouldiors, who after the contract of peace did ſtraggle and range abroad and liued vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſpoile of the poore Farmers and hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen: The lord <hi>Bartrand</hi> obtained a commiſsion of the king for to lead them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of Granada againſt the Turkes and Sarrazins. And as Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> had excommunicated all this deſperat crue of ſouldiors for their violence and robberies by them committed vnder the name and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Great companies, The lord <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trand</hi> being Generall of the Army brought them through Auingnon where Pope <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> was reſident, who immediately here vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſent one of his Cardinals vnto them for
<pb facs="tcp:184116:63"/> to know what was their demand. Vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord <hi>Bartrand</hi> ſaid, Tel our Holy father that theſe men demaund a full pardon, <hi>De culpa &amp; poena</hi> of all their ſinnes, and cheefly for them which they are now excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated for: And beſides fiue thouſand crowns for their conduct money vpon this voyage and iourney, which is to the eſtabliſhment and enlargement of the Chriſtian faith and religion. The Cardinall hauing done this meſſage to the Pope, hee gaue him this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere and ſaid: Theſe are a ſtrange kind of people that deſire both mony and abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereas we are alwaies wont to receiue mony for our pardons and obſolutions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>A worthy ſentence of</hi> Solyman <hi>the great Turke to</hi> Villiars <hi>maiſter of Rhodes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen <hi>Villiars</hi> grand-maiſter of Rhodes, was forced to yeeld the cittie and Iland of Rhodes vnto <hi>Sultan So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyman,</hi> and as hee came to the ſaid Prince to compound and agree with him vpon the taking of his leaue for his returne into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, the Turke ſpake a word vnto
<pb facs="tcp:184116:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> him anſwereable vnto his greatneſſe &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. The loſſe of citties, principalities and kingdomes, is a thing ſo common amongſt men, that it onely might ſuffice to teſtifie that wee are all ſubiect to infinite myſeries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of Pope</hi> Boniface.</head>
               <p>POpe <hi>Boniface</hi> ere he was choſen to bee Pope of Rome, vſed a very ſtrict kind of life, for his ordinary dyet was for the moſt part nothing els but a cruſt of dry bread with a cup of cold water, and in ſteed of a linnen cloth cauſed alwaies his table to be couered with a net. And being demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of his friends why he vſed ſo ſober diet, anſwered, that <hi>Panis &amp; aqua,</hi> was <hi>Vita beata.</hi> But as hee was now come to the papall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and as his ſeruants were ready to ſerue him according to his former order, away (quoth he) vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this kind of diet, for know you not that <hi>Aqua &amp; panis, eſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta canis?</hi> And further, ſaid he, ſeeue me with a napkin in ſteed of a net, for now the pray is taken. It is ſaid of this Pope, that he ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a Foxe, raigned as a lyon, and died as a dogge: for by hypocriſie hee came to that
<pb facs="tcp:184116:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> place, behaued himſelfe in his gouernement moſt cruelly, and at laſt was hanged out of a window, and ſo theſe three ſayings were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>King</hi> Alphonſus <hi>anſwere to a prodigall Gentleman.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Certain Gentleman hauing waſted and ſpent all his ſtock and patrimony vpon the pleaſure of his bodie, and moreouer being greatly indebted to his creditors who did ſue him by law and impriſonment for to come by their owne, his friends came to the king humbly requeſting his highneſſe, that it would pleaſe him to commaund that the Gentleman might not bee moleſted with impriſonment, vnto whome the king made this anſwere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> had ſpent his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:65"/> onely, it is great reaſon that his body alſo ſmart for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>An act of the Dutcheſse of Bourbon.</head>
               <p>THe Dutcheſſe of Bourbon hauing in her court a certaine waighting maid, who for loue had forgotten her ſelfe, and ſo was gotten with child: as ſhee was chidden and reprooued for her fault, ſaid to excuſe it and to ſaue her honeſty, that a Gentleman of the houſe had forced and defloured her againſt her will. The Gentleman hereupon being called for to appeare and cleare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe before the ducheſſe, ſhee finding him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:184116:65"/> ſhould neuer haue fallen into this inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, where you are in at this preſent by your owne fault and folly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of King</hi> Francis <hi>and a Frier.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRancis</hi> the firſt of that name King of Fraunce, as hee was playing at Tennis with a Frier, for whome purpoſely hee had ſent, becauſe his Maieſtie knew him to be a very good and skilfull plaier: as they had plaied together a pretty while, at laſt the Frier tooke a Ball with ſo great a dexterity and ſo good a nimbleneſſe of body that it was not done without great wondring of all the beholders. The king himſelfe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, by my truth (quoth hee) moſt brauely done of a Frier. It ſhal be of an Abbot (repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Frier vpon it) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer it ſhal ſeeme good to your grace. The king being thus twice at one time ſurpriſed by a Frier, and the Abbey of Bergomoy being vacant at that preſent, made him for them words (ſo wel and readily ſpoken) Abbot of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:66"/>
               <head>The ready wit of a Venetian Gentleman.</head>
               <p>A Young Lawyer comming before the Senate of Venice for to debate a cauſe and matter in law, partly with fear and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with ſhame, his tongue vpon the ſuddaine failed him: Many of the aſsiſtants herevpon began to laugh at him. A Gentleman there preſent not vnprouided of a pleaſant reaſon ſaid vnto them, Maruell not ſirs, that his ſpeech thus faileth him, for naturally (as the Philoſophers ſay) man apperceiuing a Wolfe ſuddenly looſeth his ſpeech, and no maruell then if this yong aduocate ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many people in this place is thus ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly taken and tongtied.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="verse_dialogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:66"/>
               <head>The verſes which the Emperor <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> ſent to the Pope, and the Popes anſwer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FRedericke <hi>Emperour of Germany, vpon his excommunication by the Pope, ſent vnto him theſe verſes.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Roma diu totubans varijs erroribus acta </l>
                  <l>Corruet &amp; mundi deſinet eſſe caput.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The Popes anſwere.</speaker>
                  <l>Niteris incaſſum nauem ſubmergere Petri: </l>
                  <l>Fluctuat, at nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mergitur illa ratis.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The Emperour.</speaker>
                  <l>Fata volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſtella<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> docent, auuim<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> volatus </l>
                  <l>Quod Fredericus ego malleus orbis ero.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The Pope.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fata volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſcriptura docet, peccata loqu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quod tibi vita breuis, poena perre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis erit.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:67"/>
               <p>The Emperour being at laſt recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled againe, and comming to Rome to ſubmit himſelfe to the Pope, as hee was thither arriued and did humble himſelfe at his feete, the Pope moſt arrogantlie treading vpon the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours ſhoulders, and vſing theſe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vnto him, <hi>Super aſpidem &amp; Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſcum ambulabis &amp; non inficient calcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum pedis tui.</hi> The Emperour moued at this extreame pride, ſaid to the Pope againe, <hi>Non tibi, ſed Petro.</hi> The Pope moſt preſumptuouſly anſwered vnto it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Et mihi &amp; Petro,</hi> and ſo diſmiſſed the Emperour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>An act of a Duke of Sauoy.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEter</hi> Duke of Sauoy as hee went to the Emperour <hi>Otto</hi> the fourth, for to giue him thankes for his lands which hee had reſtored againe vnto him, attired himſelfe in a coat halfe of male and halfe of tiſſue. The Emperour demaunding him why hee did weare ſo
<pb facs="tcp:184116:67"/> ſtraunge and diſguiſed a cote of tiſſue and halfe of male, anſwered that hee did weare the cloth of gold on his right ſide for to honour therewith his Maieſtie. And as touching my left ſide (quoth hee) it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that if any man ſeeketh to wrong or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury mee I am ready to anſwere him in anie place, and defend my ſelfe as long as a drop of blood ſhall bee remaining within mee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>
                  <hi>The anſwere which the Emperour</hi> Maximilian <hi>gaue to him that ſued vnto him for to be a gentleman.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> as he was at Bologne, a certaine Cittizen of that place being of no gentilitie, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe very rich of ſubſtance and poſſeſsions, came to the Emperour and deſired his grace that it would pleaſe him for to make him a Gentleman, ſaying that hee had wealth ynough to maintaine the ſtate of it. The Emperour anſwered him,
<pb facs="tcp:184116:68"/> ſaying. I can make thee (my friend) farre richer then thou art, but I am not able to make thee a Gentleman, for vnto this degree of honour thou muſt attaine either by thine own or els thy anceſtors vertue and valiantneſſe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="medical_advice_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:184116:68"/>
            <head>
               <hi>VICTVS ET CVLTVS ratio expoſita quatuor in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulos menſes Verſibus, Per</hi> Ioachimum Camerarium.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>JANVARIVS.</head>
               <l>MEnſis amat tepido ianidocurrcre victu,</l>
               <l>Et refici grato ſaepe liquore iubet.</l>
               <l>Vena tibi nullos exudet ſecta cruores</l>
               <l>Sed calida fas est mergere corpus aqua.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>FEBRVARIVS.</head>
               <l>Februae olus, volucreſque cibis odere paluſtres</l>
               <l>Eſseque inertifica Febre timenda ſolent.</l>
               <l>Pharmaca tunc hauri tunc ſcinde in pollice venam</l>
               <l>Et calido multum flumine membra foue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>MARTIVS.</head>
               <l>Martius humores &amp; terrae &amp; corporis auget,</l>
               <l>Tunc ratio eſt pari magna tuenda cibi</l>
               <l>Dulcia tunc proſunt acri condita ſapore.</l>
               <l>Pharmaca non proſunt venam aperire nocet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:69"/>
               <head>APRILIS.</head>
               <l>Frigore vim lente reuocat telluris. Aprilis,</l>
               <l>Tunc etiam eſt tenuis perque forata cutis.</l>
               <l>Tunc intus ſunt aucta magis ſuntque omnia plena</l>
               <l>Soluere ſe venter, vena apperire iubet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>MAIVS.</head>
               <l>Omnia iam florènt iam formoſiſsimus annus</l>
               <l>Jamque ſibi cuncti mollius eſſe volunt.</l>
               <l>Balnea nunc cole, nunc ſit pharmaca ſumere cura</l>
               <l>Et tibi nunc miſso ſanguine vena fluat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>JVNIVS.</head>
               <l>Iunius &amp; gaudet gelidis &amp; paſcitur herbis</l>
               <l>Viuifico humori tunc inimica fuge.</l>
               <l>Laetitià &amp; recreet tunc mentem blanda voluptas</l>
               <l>Affligat corpus nec medicina tuum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>IVLIVS.</head>
               <l>Aeris ignufluos intendit Iulius aeſtus</l>
               <l>Hoc brcuior ſomno tempore danda quies</l>
               <l>Balnea vitentur nec venam tangere ferro</l>
               <l>Nec dominae petulans accubuiſse velis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>AVGVSTVS.</head>
               <l>Ipſe etiam Augustus ſomnum reſtringit &amp; eſcas</l>
               <l>Et veneris cupidos gaudia ferre vetat.</l>
               <l>Pharmaca nemo bibat laceret neque corpora ferro</l>
               <l>Nec gelidas intra delicietur aquas.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>SEPTEMBER.</head>
               <l>Poma dat &amp; gratos September ab arbore fructus</l>
               <l>Tunc etiam preſso paſcere lacte caprae.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:184116:69"/>
               <l>Phaermaca nil prohibet tunc ſumere, ſcindere venam,</l>
               <l>Nec tuus externum vitet aroma cibus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>OCTOBER.</head>
               <l>Octobri offertur venatio viua, volucres:</l>
               <l>Vtere, nec dubites non tenuiſſe modum.</l>
               <l>Sic tamen vt ne oneres nimio praecordia victu.</l>
               <l>Cumque modo ſtudeas non tenuiſſe modum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>NOVEMBER.</head>
               <l>Eſſe ſalutaris perbibetur Mulſa Nouembri</l>
               <l>Gingiber &amp; dulci fiſſile melle natans.</l>
               <l>Tum neque ſaepe laues, veneris neque ſacra frequentes,</l>
               <l>Ante ſenex tempus ne videare ſuum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>DECEMBER.</head>
               <l>Juxta menſe focum calidis vtare Decembri.</l>
               <l>Tunc iaceant menſis gramina nulla tuis.</l>
               <l>Incidas capitis defenſi à frigore venam,</l>
               <l>Cinnameoque tuus fragret odore calix.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="medical_advice_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:184116:70"/>
            <head>De ratione victus ſalutaris poſt inciſam venam &amp; emiſſum ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ad Armatum Epigram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Anaſtaſij.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VEnam Armate tibi medici incidêre, timenti</l>
               <l>Neſcio ventriculi qualia damna mali.</l>
               <l>Nunc quo vita modo fuſo peragenda cruore</l>
               <l>Sitque dieta tibi qualis habenda, rogas:</l>
               <l>Illi morborum dicant Armate, periti</l>
               <l>Haec non est nostra falce metenda ſeges.</l>
               <l>Non m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſum facis &amp; cupio ex te audire diſerti</l>
               <l>Atque aliquid tua quod Pieris ornet, ais.</l>
               <l>Accipe qua idoquidem nugas ad ſeria ducis,</l>
               <l>Quae facias octo verſibus octo dies.</l>
               <l>Prima <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aena die ſit miſſo ſanguine parca:</l>
               <l>Lux abeat laetis aucta ſecunda modis</l>
               <l>Tertia ſed placidae debetur tota quieti:</l>
               <l>Quarta &amp; quinta ſibi mollius eſſe volant.</l>
               <l>Balnea ſexta petit: mox ſeptima colligit auras</l>
               <l>Fertque vagos circumrura nemuſque pedes.</l>
               <l>Octaua amplexus dilectae coniugis, &amp; quae</l>
               <l>Ante fuit, vitam reſtituiſſe ſolet.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
